All three species of North American
bears are found here,
brown bears, black bears and polar bears.
My name is Chris Morgan. I have dedicated
half my life to the study and
conservation of bears. Now, I’ve embarked upon
a 3,000 mile journey into the heart of
the Bears world with me my good friend
and filmmaker Joe Pontecorvo. You don't
notice it’s cold until you look at your
filmset and you see frost over
everything. Together
our goal is to peel back the layers of
myth and misunderstanding on this
complex creature. See our glance, I put this in
our place in it. To better understand
their personalities, all our theories out the
window to witness firsthand how they
live today
and what the future might hold for the
bears of the last frontier.
My journey has taken me through the
season of the brown bear and black bear
from an area nearly untouched by man
to the most urban environment in Alaska.
Now at the very edge of the North
American continent, a new adventure is
about to unfold.
I leave behind the cold metal and steel
of Prudhoe Bay and head to the home of
the polar bear. my plane touches down on
a four-mile long windswept strip of land
known as Barter Island on the edge of
the Beaufort Sea. Fewer than 300
residents mostly Inupiat Eskimo call
this remote island home but they are not
alone.
They share this frigid coastline with another
great hunter, the polar bear.
While the rest of the bears have denned
up for winter, polar bears sense the
change in season and are anxious for the
chill to set in.
Polar bears are ice loving creatures
and from an early age they are drawn to it,
investigating any new formations on the
water.
What fascinating to me about these
polar bears is that there's some finally
tuned and adapted to life of ice.
This looks like a bear is running right
down this trail here and he's broken
through here. Look it’s paw actually
broken through this ice here. In fact the ice
starts to form already, so there forever
testing the ice conditions to see if
it's firm enough for them to head out
onto and it's not yet obviously.
As adults they depend upon ice to hunt.
Unlike brown bears, polar bears are
highly specialised carnivores and hunt
almost exclusively one animal, seals.
The ringed seal look nervously around,
exposed on this open expanse but without
thermal advice this bear has little
chance to hunt down the seal.
Tt's late October and by now the ocean
should be frozen over.
But this year, winter has come late. Part
of the Laguna covered with ice, but the
ocean has yet to be tamed. For now, the
bears are trapped on land unable to hunt
Locals call this area the polar bear
campground.
It's a nursery of swords, a safe haven
for mothers and young. This time of year
when other polar bears are waiting for
sea ice to form, pregnant females are
waiting for enough snow to dig their
maternity dens. This whole area in fact
is really important for denning females
when they're pregnant they come and give
birth in the habitat along this coast
here near the Arctic National Wildlife
Refuge. So many the females return to
the same area to raise their cubs.
They seem to have this recognition when
the cubs playing, females playing and
one cub is playing with another cub.
From its, it's quite the interesting
scenario that's going on.
That guy make a beeline right for us.
Actually we've only been here a few
minutes and already we've attracted some
attention.
I'm directly up win from her. She got
her nose in the air and she can catch my
scent.
And she's coming this way, we probably won't
have a very long before we have to make
a hasty retrieve. You know the most
predatory of the bears and there is
capable of great speed is grizzly bears
are. You know they can run 35 miles an
hour so.
I think it's time to get in the boat.
She’s moving over here with some
determination. We need to make a retrieve here.
You want to jump on go?
Yeah, it looks like it's getting a really
agitated, she can mile us but she can't
access us,can't figure out for a meal or
not and it's how they live their lives.
They are curious predators. Everything
about them is about surviving the cold
and hunting seals. Being a specialist,
the key to surviving the Arctic, it is
true for the bears as it is for the
Inupiat Eskimos.
Centuries these two hunters of the
Arctic of, made their living from the
ocean. The lives connected by the animals
they hunt. Twice a year in spring and for
the Inupiat Eskimos hunt bowhead whales
to discard it remains are left on this
bone pile.
Seven o'clock in the morning would wear
on the outskirts of town and there's a
good spot to wait for bears right here
because there seemed to like coming out
of the cover of darkness.
Sometimes it's a case of waiting around
a long time for themselves are what we doing
right now. Let's see if any show up,
fingers crossed.
This guy is some, closes we want to
get. The whale meat with high fat content
may help some bears get through these
tough times when there's little else to
eat. If warming trends continue,
competition for this small pile of food
could get fierce for a species already
on the brink. Polar bears will have some
tough times ahead.
An overnight snow flurry leaves fresh
drift for this young arctic fox to play
in.
The icy lagoon is full of activity, the
bears use this new platform to practice
their light as a feather walk. Sea-ice
unlike fresh water ice is flexible which
gives the bears a lot to experiment with.
The fibres baleen whales used to filter
their food has become the perfect toy
for these young cubs.
yeah
Play attracts attention and quickly
their mom claims the large baleen to
strip out what she can from it.
With the bone pile nearly exhausted, this
mother frantically digs for scrapped
buried in the snow, but her fine soon
draws attention from another family.
Tensions are high as bears uncover every
last bit of whalebone, scraping what meat
they can from the bones.
I find like this is worth protecting
and this mother bear is not about to
give up her meal so easily.
This young bear will have to seek out
his own meal.
Fortunately for him, the weather appears
to be getting worse.
Temperatures have dipped to a
bone-chilling 20 degrees below. Greece
ice is starting to cover the water
and winds batter the tiny island.
The town is battening down the hatches
as the storm sets in. Once ice begins to
form, the ocean freezes over in just a
few days.
Winter has finally taken hold, the town
now in its final days of sunlight. It's
farewell to the bears as they head out
onto the pack ice to hunt.
The Sun will vanish below the horizon
and not reappear for another two months.
For now, the world is in darkness.
Miles out on the pack ice, polar bears
are hunting seals, stalking their prey
and the inky blackness of winter.
Near the end of January, the Sun begins
to reappear.
I.t’s a time of transition
with more light each day.
And by May in mid-Spring, the sun is up
24 hours a day
and it's safe enough for us to venture
out onto the pack ice.
We nearly eight miles out on a thin
shelf of ice
searching for polar bears,
but I'd be foolish to attempt this alone.
Dale Brower grew up on the North
Slope. Maybe we'll get on a high point look
around.
Meaning he grew up in a world completely
alien to most of us.
He's a really fresh because that
actually on top of our sledtracks from
about five hours ago, maybe even four
hours ago, so they weren't here then
that's for sure.
He might have heard the snow machine and
then kind of snuck back off into this
these pressure ridges here and he could
just be hiding out in these. In this
featureless white landscape, it's the
bears to have the advantage. Problem is
if they're off in the distance right
there behind the ice to get easily
obscured even a large animal like a
polar bear. Is this a weather front
coming in here?
Yeah, that's actually the water sky
that's their water from the open lead
reflecting into the sky. So if you had it into
those clouds, you find open water?
Open a water underneath. And there's
a good chance for the polar bears that
we’re tracking here.
Tt's been an exhaustive search and still
the bear remains elusive.
Why are you checking which way the winds
blow? Just so the entry way is on the
opposite end. All right. We don't want it
facing the wind right? I guess that's
really important when it blew it for 50
miles an hour everyday. I can already
set the tent. Our camp is modest but
functional in every way. I'm discovering
there's little that Dale does that
doesn't relate directly to our own
survival even the caribou hide seemed to
be the perfect insulation against the
cold.
Yeah kinda yeah good fits in a little better
like it’s a big photo
Huh white. What is that?
That's my full of here. It's the best
for out there as if it's for keeping
the wind out.
Oh yeah, it keeps the wind out and then it
doesn't really, it doesn't frost so it
doesn't collect snow and stuff.
Interesting. And then it stays pretty
clean even though you get it dirty, can
just wipe it in the snow and the hair
will just clean itself, basically like a
polar bear after its done with its kill.
Just rubbing the snow, take a snow bath
and then just take all the dirt off
fur.
Polar bears are stealth hunters and just
because you don't see them, doesn't mean
they're not there. See what we can do,
I’ll break my ankles.
Yeah, perfect vantage point as I was
saying the perfect vantage point for
looking for polar bears are cameras
right here, it's easy to forget this mack
bank right in the middle of polar bear
habitat. All the way to the horizon, all I
can see is ice, giant jagged peaks and
troughs of ice as far as you can see and
it is a barren hostile landscape if you
can't read the ice here, you're not going
to survive.
Polar bears are masters at reading the
ice, patrolling the edge of a lead,
smelling for any trace of a seal.
But sneaking up on a seal in open water
is a challenge, even for a polar bear.
The best chance for a meal is to sniff
out a seal’s breathing hole or even a den
with seal pups.
It's a rare sight but Dale has observed
polar bears hunting, like these there
is a hole here that barrel, which is
like that. If the hole is here, he
could smell it and he will close the hole
and then dig this side out where the
seal is at and it will scoop the seal
out. It's one of the earliest instinctive
behaviours for polar bear cubs. While
their mom rests, these cubs will practice
what it takes to become the apex
predator of the Arctic. Learning to lead
with your nose,
investigate anything out of the ordinary,
leap across unstable chunks of ice and
of course the belly flop. But when Mom
huffs, the cubs know it's time to
continue with the real hunt.
Polar bear tracks have led us here
A whaling camp perched at the edge of a
lead. A bear was spotted just a day ago,
perhaps the very one we're looking for.
For the Inupia, well-hunting is an ancient
way of life that continues nearly
unchanged today.
With 24 hours of light the rhythm of
life is set by the whales,
not the Sun. Whale hunting is by far
the most dangerous part of their
subsistence life and these young people
are doing it just the way that their
ancestors did. These guys are like 20, 22
years old and have each got a role and
it’s importance to the community is vital.
We are when you become a captain and
it's your first whale and you give the whole
thing away to all the whaling cruise. You
just learned over time that what you
catch isn't really yours as a hunter
you're here to feed the town and
the families, not really for yourself.
Ihe new PS commitment to this tradition
is help to keep this part of the
coastline free of oil development.
Without their protection, this vital
habitat may disappear completely.
Whale off in the background blow hole there.
Wow
Maybe our wait is over as the whale
approaches, the camp becomes dead silent
As soon as the whale surfaces, the boat
is launched.
It's a tense moment as the men paddle
towards the massive whale, somewhere just
under the surface. Harpooning a whale by
hand is extremely dangerous,
bowhead whales can weigh 60 tons. One
swipe of its enormous tail fluke could
easily crush the tiny craft.
Because incredible system we were there trying
to get the whale out of the water. We dug two
holes through the ice that go right through
and they're gonna see the block and
tackle and they’ll be a able to hold the whale in.
This bowhead whale will feed several
families throughout the season and
perhaps the polar bears as well. It’s a
cycle of life that has remained
unchanged for thousands of years. Other
whales will continue their annual
migration, following the open leads east
to their summer grounds in the Beaufort
Sea. But the ice is too thin for us to go
any further.
It's late May and the pack ice is slowly
retreating. Right now,
it certainly feels treacherous out here,
doesn't it?
There are no shortcuts in the Arctic, you
have to know when to call it quits. As
Dale often says if you don't come back
this season,
you can't hunt next season.
It's a good lesson even for a polar bear.
But continually having to hold himself
onto the ice takes an immense amount of
energy, polar bears face this challenge
every spring for the impacts of a
warming world have made matters worse.
Lots of pack ice is estimated eleven
percent per decade.
The bears’ fragile hunting platform is
getting thinner and this mother and
cub found themselves
in an ocean of melting ice.
And if warming trends continue, seems
like this will become common.
Like many animals that have made such
great leaps in their evolution to
survive, the world may be changing too
fast for polar bears to keep up with.
While the endless Arctic Sun slowly
erodes the ice, it brings renewed life to
the tundra
and the season of the Grizzly has only
just begun.
It's the perfect time to head South and
into the heart of the Brooks Range. There’s like
a perfect valley for grizzly bears. Well,leave it and
find it now, okay? We pick this spot was a grizzly.
We're following the caribou trails of
great migrations from seasons past.
It’s absolutely cover with caribou trails right up
the mountains, right over the ridges, one valley
to the next and we're hoping
these caribou tracks will point the way
to Arctic Grizzlies. It may be our best
chance at a closer look at this elusive
predator. But finding nearly
half-a-million caribou in the vastness
of the Western Arctic takes patience and
persistence. We picked this spot because it
caribou trails all around down either
valley, each side of the tent here.
No single caribou yet and not a single
bear but hopefully when the caribou
arrived which they could in big numbers
and the bear may arrive as well. That's
that's what we're hoping for.
We've enlisted the aid of aerial
cameraman Daniel’s apps to help document
the herd and hopefully the bears if we
find them. So based on what Jim from
fishing games said, he said that the
females and calves are running along
this line here to the North. Ok. And this
is also where he expects will see the
bears, but it's really unpredictable.
It's completely unpredictable. Caribou
you never know where they're gonna go.
Caribou are the ultimate wanderers.
Within a single year, the Western Arctic
Herd will range across a quarter of
Alaska, an area the size of Montana.
Oh, right there. Right there, huge herd of caribous
all by the river. Wow, there must be at least a hundred
maybe a hundred fifty there. Oh, how fast you count.
Okay. Oh, that’s a good sign. Our first caribou.
It looks like we're in luck, we've just
caught the tail end of a massive herd.
Wow we have just settled down in a spot
here, so we're trying to stay very quiet,
reduce our silhouette on the horizon
because they're just so ever vigilant you
know for wolves and grizzly bears that's
where the safety in number comes from.
If you're eating, you're not watching.
You're watching, you're not eating.
So if you're in a group, you can do both.
Spring is carving season and some of
these newborns are just a few days old.
Caribou calves can run within hours of
being born.
It's a matter of survival.
Newly born calves are most vulnerable to
predators and they have to stay close to
mom at all times.
Wolves are never far behind
This grey wolf is testing the herd,
looking for any signs of weakness.
He's joined by another from the pack,
together they've cut the herd in half.
but soon the herd has regrouped and the
wolves give up the chase.
There's little rest for the herd until
they complete their seasonal migration
to their summer range.
Caribou are largely sustained by the
high-energy sugars found in Arctic
lichen. So priced is this plant that many
biologists believe the availability of
lichen during the winter months can
profoundly impact caribou numbers.
Well the caribou, this landscape wouldn't
look the way it does they aerate the
soil as they're walking to make it more
productive for plants, even their hair
provides nesting material for migratory
birds around here and you can imagine
how much fertiliser half-a-million
caribou create, like blood vessels
flowing across this giant landscape.
Wow, look at that, the mom with three cubs.
These are spring cubs in their first
year of life foraging along the hillside.
Arctic Grizzlies must make the most of
these short summers and that includes
this mating pair that have somehow found each
other in this vast expanse. Grizzlies
must cover great distances just to find
enough food. At Arctic Grizzly, an open
tundra can have a home range the size of
Yellowstone. Once you touch down, keeping
up with the Grizzly is nearly impossible.
For the caribou, their journey is nearly
over. The herd has finally made it to
their summer range, the completion of
their journey. But caribou are wanderers
and they don't stay put for long.
With the herd moving on and only
fleeting glimpses of grizzlies, we are
left with few choices.
An old report of a salmon run has given
us some hope.
Well, I mean I think this is far inland. It looks
like a good one, don’t you? But this far inland, it's a
long shot, even if we find salmon in the
river.
No one I’ve spoken with is actually seen
Arctic Grizzlies fishing.
The caribou torned me but it's not them
I’m looking for. Finding bear signs is the
priority here.
But if grizzlies are around, it’s best to
be prepared.
I carry a shotgun only as an extreme
precaution.
And believe it or not, they're really
popular thing with cranky bear is this
Hedysarum root. They love this stuff.
I'm surprised this morsel has been left actually.
You might look at this place and
think it doesn't offer
very much but they piece together a diet.
Little bit by little bit they get by
here. The tracks all through here. Look at
this fresh grizzly bear tracks and then
right in front of it
caribou track. So both of these species
are using this river to get from A to B
and occasionally if a bear is lucky, they will
have to prey on a caribou especially
during the carving season.
Wow look at that, the salmon are running.
The question is where are the bears.
Really time for a cup of coffee I think.
After hours of waiting, there's a shadow
moving through the willows.
oh yeah, that’s right.
There's a third cub coming up the river. Okay,
I see here.
She's crossing here, I do not want to
surprise this bear though. Artic
Grizzlies have a much more aggressive
reputation than coastal brown bears. She
seems pretty cool.
She seen us. Just finding one would be
chance enough. How far back as the third
one, right behind the second. Okay.
The fourth one is way back there in the
willows on this side of the creek. But
now, we suddenly surrounded by four.
The family seems to be using the river
as a corridor but their food is buried
in the tundra.
Hedysarum roots are an important source
of protein for Arctic Grizzlies. The
bears lack of interest and the salmon is
possling but these chum salmon don't
have nearly the fat and calories as
those the bears eat along the coast. Once
they leave the saltwater to head
upstream, they stop eating. All their
energy goes into reaching the spawning
ground where they were born. For these
fish that's roughly 400 river miles.
after weeks of swimming upstream, they've
used a tremendous amount of their
reserves to get here and the ones
vibrant colour has faded from their skin.
Males will gather and fight for position
as females arrive.
Once this courting process starts, it can
take hours or even days to complete.
The family has returned but this time
they've staked out a spot on the river.
Mom is completely focused on fishing.
She's landed a huge chum salmon.
The whole family retreats into the
willows to share the fish. Here in the
Arctic a catch like this is quite a
bounty. Mom quickly returns to the
river's edge. The cubs will pick this
fish clean while mom looks for more.
Look at those cubs, all lined up waiting for
mom to catch dinner.
She's quickly proving to be a skilled
fisher and by the looks of these cubs,
she's been an excellent provider for the
first two and a half years of their
lives.
It's hard, it's hard to even imagine that was
cubs. They're almost as big as she is at
this state.
The Cubs have been watching her closely
and now instead of feasting off what
she's caught, they seem to be interested
in learning to fish themselves.
These new experiences show off how
different each of these cubs are. They’re
all individuals. This cub has plenty of
confidence.
His borderline troublesome. Close enough,
that’s close enough.
It’s okay it’s alright. Seem good.
It's alright. he ventures much further
than the other two and seems to be quite
bold. This boldness concerns his mom
quite a bit, but it's also what yields
him his first catch. Very nice. That's
great. They're learning, they got it. Ya.
When he catches something, it's his alone.
He is already showing his independence.
The other two cubs are more plush and
cub like than their brother. One is
playful and anxious as he bounds into the
water after fish. The other cub is much
more cautious, sticking close to mom.
For the first time in the days we've
been watching her, she's able to rest
comfortably on the shore while the cubs
patrol the shallow river. It's doubtful
they know this is their last summer
under her care and guidance.
At last her smallest cub is beginning to
focus on the salmon. Mom follows close
behind stirring up the fish.
She gives up the chase, letting her cub
finish the catch. Oh look at that. It’s
not uncommon to see a mother get very
protective and aggressive while fishing.
To me, she seems intent on preparing
these cubs for life on their own as she
does with finding food.
Don't forget we're here. After several
days of being watched, her curiosity for
us has finally peaked. Hey bear, you are a
good mama, ah you are so sweet.
Ah look at her back up like that. But
we're gonna get out of your way.
And that's our cue.
We'll take a cue from this. A good lesson
for us to keep in mind is to always
leave on a good note.
While it may be some time before they
come across people again when they do, we
want their memory of us to be a positive
one.
With a few short huffs, she rounds up
her family to call it a day.
We really didn't know we entered this
situation if she was going to be
accepting of us or not
and she's emerged to be this wise, mature,
thoughtful, careful female. It's taken us
time to get to know them and to
understand that, so we know what their
limits are and it reminds you that any
two bears are as different as any two
people you might encounter.
And over this journey, it's become clear.
The world these bears inhabit is vast.
That it must remains so to sustain such
great wondrous.
The resources we so priced are embedded
in the land that sustains all life here.
Like the great plains of Africa,
Alaska is the last stronghold for some
of the Earth's wildest creatures.
I've never felt so comfortable or so
alive as i do here.
This may be the end of my journey, but
Alaska's wilderness and its wildest
creatures
will always call me back.
To learn more about what you've seen on
this nature program visit pbs.org.