The tiger, iconic symbol of the wild and
an apex predator that we fear and admire.
In our imaginations, they roam the jungle,
but today many tigers have never even
seen the wild.
The vast majority of them spend their
lives in captivity.
Princess is an American tiger, a distant
relative of her wild ancestors.
She doesn't even know how to hunt.
Most Tigers in America aren't found in
zoos,
they're privately owned.
There are more than twice as
many of them as the highly endangered
wild tiger.
This could change if new legislation has
passed. That would ban the private
ownership in breeding the tigers.
What are the issues surrounding captive
tigers in America and what does the
future hold for their wild cousins?
Tigers are one of the world's most
popular animals.
Everybody loves to see a tiger at the
zoo,
even the scientists to work around them
are impressed by the majesty.
Ron Tilson is the senior conservation
advisor at the Minnesota Zoo and a
renowned expert on tigers.
He spent many years tracking and
studying them in the jungles of Asia.
My heart beats faster every time I see
one.
Yeah there is a ... It's because everything...
they represent everything. They are the
icon of Asian wilderness, they are the
most powerful cat, the largest cat.
They are in my opinion one of the most
attractive cats. But it's also the fact
that essentially we have evolved as a
species with the tiger and the tiger is
one of the only animals on earth that
praise and eats people
and when a tiger looks at a human being.
I think the tiger sees us for exactly
what we are, we are nothing more than a
piece of meat.
The tiger and the power it represents
has always fascinated us. At the
beginning of the 20th century,
there are 100,000 tigers in the forests
of Asia.
The first tiger came to America as
entertainers before Susans Circuses
attempted to control their breeding
surplus animals found their way into
private hands.
Soon everyone from the rich and famous
to companies in sports teams wanted a
piece of the big cat. For some Americans
like the character of Tony Montana and
the movie Scarface, owning a tiger became
a symbol of success.
Martin Dinnes is a celebrity veterinaria
and was one of the first to specialize
in exotic animals. His talent and
reputation
let him to work for a-list stars like
Michael Jackson and the magicians
Siegfried and Roy. He witnessed first-hand
the rise of the tiger population in
America. The tiger pet phenomenon became
a trend I would say in the early sixties.
We could be driving in Beverly Hills and
see a person driving a convertible with
a tiger sitting up in the back seat. Or
people owning a jagwar, a big jaguar
driving around a new jaguar with it.
There were no import restrictions, there
were no restrictions on the sale of pet
shop of these kind of animals. You know a
little tiger cub is nice and cute,
so people thought it would be
fashionable, it was unique,
they can show it off and it was trendy
then. The pet tiger phenomenon may have
existed briefly in other parts of the
world but it never had the dimensions
it's taken on in America. In the nineteen
seventies actress, Tippi Hedren, the star
of Alfred Hitchcock "The Birds" and
Bart done an unusual film project.
She starred in the moving "Roar",
where actors and crew members rub
shoulders with dozens of lions and
tigers.
I can't believe we did all that
that we were foolish enough to do it, so
many of us were hurt.
You know that it was, you know of
insanity.
It was truly insane in here. Tippi Hedren
radically changed.
She converted the "Roar" movie set into
the Shambala Preserve, a sanctuary for
abused and neglected big cats. Her strong
stance against private ownership has
drawn attention to the issues facing
captive and wild big cats. In the wild
tigers are threatened by habitat
destruction and human encroachment.
They've been hunted and poached for
their skins.
Most of all they suffered from the
illegal trade of their parts for use in
traditional medicine.
Ninety-seven percent of the species have
been wiped out over the last hundred
years and with only 320 hundreds wild tigers
left.
They are facing a total crisis.
This just about everything has been
tried and just about everything is
failed. Everyone is trying to think
through how to go about making a future
for tigers and the bottom line is that we
failed in every, every example. There
is no one place you can put your finger
and say "AHA, here's the magic formula on
how to save tigers."
Tigers have been on the endangered
species list since it was established. In
1973 it became illegal to import tigers
born in the wild,
so the tigers living in the United
States today are American, born and
raised. The population of captive tigers
has been steadily growing. In the wild,
a female spends a couple of years
teaching her three or four cubs how to
hunt and fend for themselves. But in
captivity,
she can breed every year. Today most
American Tigers are privately owned and
some people still keep them as pets.
Zuzana Kukol and Scott Shoemaker
live in the small town of Pahrump Nevada
with their six tigers.
It's your definition of pet is something
you throw food at and it's nice and
docile.
Okay then that's not a tiger. That's my
girl, that's my girl.
In the cage, it's just fun. Outside
that van it's like, okay we are going for
the walk, we are going to go for the
training,
the outside is like you're in school. In
the cage, it's ok, it's their place, it's
their home.
So basically that's the Golden Rule,
you don't push them into any set of
training in the cage and you will never
ever turn the back on a tiger. But not
all captive tigers are pets or
collectors' items. Some private owners see
themselves as conservationists and
believe America is the Tigers Noah's Ark.
Patty Perry runs her own center for
conservation and education in Southern
California.
She is also the Vice-President of the
Feline Conservation Federation, the
largest organization promoting private
ownership and breeding of captive exotic
cats in the United States.
It's far from perfect but in our world
today we have to have a captive breeders,
private captive breeders,
we have to have private educators,
because the zoos can't do it all.
You don't get that kind of contact and
that kind of one on one at a zoo.
They have been poached, they have been
hunted for their pelts and for their
internal organs and we have very very
low populations.
This is Prana, the standard.
The snow white is Vishnu. This is my
little red-headed stepchild and this is
the one
the golden tabby. He's gonna be our
biggest tiger here.
The Tigers is very much an emotional
bond. They they respond emotionally. I, I
got them all as babies, so I bottle raise
them.
So there is that connection you know,
they identify me is, you know like mom
with milk. Who wants to feed a tiger?
I kind of started on this and give you guys a
chance. I want you to hold the stick, just
hold the stick and put it right through
there. Right.
These cats being six generations, you
know captive bred and their, you know,
their their primary contact being human
beings are not going to be the same as a
cat that's in the wild, it's a completely
different animal.
But i will there be domesticated know
they're wild animals.
The wild nature of tigers is seen even
among those in captivity. In 2003, famous
Las Vegas entertainer,
Roy Hrn was mauled during the performance
by one of his beloved tigers.
Tigers just grab him like would
be right around here in this area
grabs and like just locks on him, mix
them up and just drags. And we just heard
all these commotion behind the
curtain and you could hear. It reminded
everyone that even trained tigers are
unpredictable and dangerous. For 40 years,
those guys did two to three shows a day,
in the beginning seven days a week.
That's a lot of exposure to a tiger. You
fall down and finally these big cats and
especially with tigers
they're gonna carry you regardless of
what your relationship. He's got
a thing for me, Patty.
I know he does. In my career as a
zoological veterinarian, I worked the
gamut of facilities and owners that have
tigers.
There's the zoos, there's the circuses, there's the
private collectors and years ago there
were a lot more of the illicit owners of
these animals but I've worked for all of
them and I don't I don't discriminate. I
have done the best I can to discourage
reading by unqualified individuals, but I
I took an oath and isn't my business to
say no I'm not going to treat this tiger
because you own it privately.
That's that's on the other side of
medicine for me.
Lisa Ann Tekancic is an attorney in
Washington DC. Her organization, The Wild
Cat Conservation Legal Aid Society, is
trying to determine the exact number of
privately-owned tigers. Here calling a
follow up with you on the tiger research
you were going to finalize some of the
numbers for what state are you still
working on, what are looking at, alavema?
The actual number of tigers in the
United States is still a matter of
speculation, but the enforcement of laws
already in place is problematic.
Legislation varies from state to state.
At the federal level, the Department of
Agriculture and the Department of
Interior both enforce different laws
affecting tigers.
There is no single government body
responsible for tiger welfare.
Well, we don't really know how many
tigers are held captive in the United
States is a very good question because
estimates tend to go all over. Some say
there's five thousand cats and captivity
tigers,
some say there's up to ten. The problem
with the numbering system is that the
two federal agencies that are there to
enforce our endangered species act and
the
the welfare and don't know how many
tigers are out there, which is very
troubling, because we need to get a
handle on the number of cats. As hard as
it is to imagine,
big cats can be found everywhere
even on the fifth floor of an apartment
building in the heart of New York City,
like on an October day in 2003. This
police video shows me all grown
325-pound tiger left home alone by its
owner in unit 5-feet of the Harlem
apartment building.
If the number in the location of big
cats is a source for concern, a
larger concern might just be the
irresponsible owners,
screening for them remains difficult.
In 2005 near the Ronald Reagan
Presidential Library in Moorpark, a
stunning example of human tiger conflict
occurred.
It's not a tiger, right there was real,
slow,
huge is about this high up to the fence.
Newly retired George Gross was the
incident commander at the California
Fish and Game Department. For more than
three weeks,
he chased a tiger on the loose in a
residential area.
He got no help from the cat's owner and
on a February morning he had a difficult
decision to make.
Basically this was like the city living
in fear for a month, because somewhere
there was this large tiger running
around in their neighbourhood.
We didn't see it for quite a while but
we knew it was in here,
so when it climbed out it was like it
came out of nowhere all of a sudden.
Everybody could see it and it started
walking around quite slowly through the
grass.
You know I was within a hundred fifty
yards of there, first thing I thought was
“What a majestic animal! This thing's
beautiful.” But then you know I came back
in as,
but I have this job.
You do too.  So it started walking towards
me and then it started going up a trail and
it sat there and I can't have it up
here on the soccer field, baseball field.
In our opportunity to take a shot
really diminishes, so that's when I gave
the order for people with rifles
to. If they had a clean shot, to take the
shot. The male tiger weighs as much as 600
pounds was taken from the hills near the
Ronald Reagan Presidential Library by
wildlife officials, who say they had no
choice but to kill it.
I'm always felt that like unfortunately I
made the right decision and you know to
be honest is the first thing I did was
paddle and say I'm sorry, because
I knew I didn't want to kill him.
George Gross was not the last law
enforcement agent faced with such a
decision,
there was an even more dramatic incident
in October 18 2011 when there was a
massive release of wild animals in Zanesville
Ohio farm. The owner of a private Zoo
threw open the gates of his facility
before committing suicide
This time it wasn't one tiger but 18 on
the loose.
They were all killed by the authorities
along with lions, bears and monkeys.
It probably will come to another tragedy
before certain laws are either in force
like they should be or new laws are
going to have to be implemented to have
multiple situations happen because we're
not moving on these issues is very
tragic and it's very sad not only for
the individuals but the cats that are
involved because most of time those cats
are shot on site.
I'd rather see us being a proactive
mode versus a reactive mode.
It’s the time to ban the private ownership
of tigers and other exotic animals.
26 states banned the private ownership
of tigers but in many states
it's still legal to own and breed them if
you have a permit. Stories of tiger cub
sold at swap knees or on the internet
are galvanising the movement to band
private ownership of big cats and in
Washington a political and legal battle
is underway.
People can't believe that these animals
are still being born to be sold as pets
and you can get them for any amount of
money if you’re foolish enough to pay.
And when you see those little Cubs, its
they're cute. But by the time they're
seven months old, they are tearing up
your house and taking a pretty good
chunk out of you because they don't have
a 400-pound mum to say “Nock it off.”
nor do they have any siblings with them
to play. So you become the sibling and
they’re tough.
You're dealing with an apex predator.
They are top of the food chain, wanted
for the most dangerous animals in the
world and yet our government says that's
ok and they will even give a permit to
have these apex killers and somebody's
backyard
it's very wrong. Tippi Hedren decided
that something needed to be done and
contacted her congressman. She
successfully proposed a new law to
prevent taking big cats across state
lines but this was just the beginning.
So I took a available to Washington in
2003.
I was simply to stop these animals
moving from one state to another and it
took two years. It was called a title “The
Captive Wildlife Safety Act” was sort of
a precursor to the bill that I I am
ultimately, my goal is to have a bill
that would stop the breeding of all of
these animals to be sold as a pet or for
financial gain.
Tippi Hedren isn't alone in her quest to
end the private ownership and breeding
of tigers,
conservation organisations fear that the
captive population of America tigers
could contribute to the lucrative global
trade and tiger parts for traditional
medicines.
For now, tiger farms in China
and poaching are the main source of the
parts.
To have a state law and we have 50
states banning breeding of tigers in
captivity would be too problematic and
it's easier to make it a federal
regulation then we don't have 50
different laws that could have as many
different exemptions, so it's easier to
do it at the federal level. The private
ban is really focused on going after
the individuals are these backyard
breeders that are sort of out of the
radar. Many private owners who have all
their permits believe they have every
right to keep tigers. While the
possibility of a federal ban would be a
nightmare,
there are more and more and more
restrictions all the time, all the time.
More and more regulations and more and
more restrictions. You
you have to again you have to be
organized, you have to have love it, you
have to present your side of it to the
right people.
It's a political thing, it's a money
thing.
The organisation is pushing for the ban
are also concerned about tiger welfare
even federal agencies have set very low
standards of care. A 3 by 3 meter cage is
the minimum requirement.
Timmy Thies manages the wild cat
sanctuary in Minnesota.
She has heard countless stories of abused
animals and careless owners. Most of the
animals including the tigers at the
sanctuary come from people who think a
tiger would make a good pet.
We hear all the stories. They got
aggressive, it turned on me.
I can't find vet care, I lost my
homeowner's insurance.
You know I didn't know what get this big.
I did not know it eat this much and we tell
people a wild animal is not a pet and it
never should be kept as one.
Tighten behind me that tiger was
illegally owned and should have been
seized under the state law.
Had he been seized prior to that? His
owner would still be alive today.
Stopping people from acquiring and
breeding tigers motivates animal rights
defenders and conservationists but
private readers defend their practice by
saying that if tigers were to go extinct
in the wild
it would be better to have captive
tigers than none at all. This view is
highly controversial.
My question is “If you been these animals,
we can no longer keep them breed them. So
it will be, they will be extinct in
captivity.”
Now they go extinct in the wild. What have
you accomplished?
You killed the species.
A ban on breeding are keeping tigers has
broad implications,
while the United States looks to control
unregulated greeting of tigers by
private owners across the world.
Extraordinary efforts are being made to
save tigers in the wild.
Varane Tilson, zoo tigers represent a
backup for the wild population.
He has been the coordinator of the tiger
species survival plan designed to
maintain healthy and genetically diverse
tigers. In this world we try to have what
we call a hands-off management
that means let's not touch tigers, let's
not play with tigers,
let's consider them really quite
dangerous. For the longest time I refused
to even call a tiger by a name.
I'm not particularly fond of house names
and to me they’re numbers. They’re stud
book number and I see a tiger more as a
collection of jeans and what I'm
concerned about is the future way down
the line that these animals still
maintain their tigers.
Scientists have divided tigers in 29
sub-species. Three of them have already
gone extinct.
The Bali tiger in the nineteen forties,
the Caspian tiger in the nineteen
seventies and the Javan tiger in the
nineteen eighties.
Surviving are the Siberian or Amur
tiger. The Bengal, the Indochinese, the
Malayan and the Sumatran tigers, they are
all endangered
and the last South China tigers can only
be found in captivity.
We know every tiger in the North
American zoos and we know its’ lineage.
We know every parent, grandparent
great-grandparent,
great-great-grandparent all the way
back to its wild-caught mother and
father.
So we know exactly where they came from
in Russia for the more Tigers and we
know who they made it with and who their
offspring, so we have these like giant
family trees.
Unlike most zoos, most private owners
don't know the lineage of their tigers
because no one has kept track of their
pedigrees.
Yeah there you go over. Tigers from
different subspecies resemble each other
and most breeders are interested in
keeping subspecies pure. As for
subspecies,
I I don't believe in them. I don't care
and some of them might have more bangle
blood in them because some of them don't
actually grow that big dick for inventor.
Some of them do, so i know that a lot of
Siberian blood with them.
The white tiger is the best example of
breeding for looks. Loved for its
striking appearance.
It's not a subspecies but a colour morph,
the result of a recessive gene that
causes one in every 10,000 tigers to be
born white. White tigers are almost
non-existent in the wild but they are
often bred in captivity.
This is made them highly in bred and more
susceptible to health problems and
that's not the only consequence of
private ownership. People notice that many
tigers in captivity might be bigger than
in the wild. As in the wild, you need to stay
athletic to catch prey. In captivity, they
get their food served basically a silver
platter and I know there isn't many
tigers in captivity are huge,
they're simply fat. They are obese, not
good for their liver. Lots of the stuff,
American tigers are fed.
It's basically start feed, it is from
supermarket. Some of the meat might have
some hormones in them.
The other territories, somebody might
selectively breed for bigger size
because it looks impressive and display
huge tiger. It looks more impressive than
small tiger. Might be simply because they
just don't exercise as much as the ones
in a wild because any cat you can.