What our loot of one is acquired temple
set in the remote countryside of
northern Thailand. The nine monks who
live here belong to a strict buddhist
sect, dedicated to a life of simplicity
and purity.
They live at peace with the world hidden
away and the natural wilderness of
Thailand's last woodlands.
But this is a monastery like no other. I
was born in the tiger year 1951, the
Chinese year is tiger year.
The forest monk at this ministry share
their lives with 11 tigers.
Every day, these self-trained keepers
devote their lives to looking after
these huge animals.
It is a unique site,
the monks control their tigers with
gentle coaxing, mutual trust and a lot of
respect.
The monks love their tigers, the tigers
love the monks. The abbot shampoo sit
strolls around his ministry with the
calm serenity of a man totally at peace
with himself. He has been in charge of
the monastery from the beginning long
before the first tigers arrived.
25 years ago, Shampoo Sit was diagnosed
with leukemia,
he had two years before the cancer would
take his life, he decided to devote
himself to buddhist meditation, and now
the cancer has gone into remission. His
second chance has given him a zest for
life and more importantly a love for all
living things.
This is my monastery, I have
11 tigers. All of animals here,
they come by themselves. And I
rescue them, and protect them and feed
them. The first thing that I have is a
chicken and peacock, deer, horse, cow, buffalo,
barking deer, reindeer, and some of the
mountain goats. There is even a leopard
which arrived one day injured as a
cub, now to use to humans,
it cannot be released. But it is the
bigger cats that are still the most
distinguished guests. Are you meaning
storm and safer meaning Thunder? With the
first to tiger cubs to arrive at the
monastery, now full-grown these two
refugees and the forests can remember no
other life than this peaceful
coexistence with the abbot, but their
lives were not always this contented.
I got him from the Muslim people.
Karin Muslim people. They bring them from
the border pass.
The border pass with Burma is a remote
and timeless wilderness.
Ethnic tribes people shy and elusive
Korean hill tribes, he can't in existence
living as they have done unchanged for
centuries.
Almost five years ago, a group of current
found young storm and thunder very near
death forest.
Their parents had been killed by poachers
and the helpless cubs have been badly
beaten and then left to die.
And the forest department police come to
tell the Karin, you can bring the tiger and
give it to me. And I'm very good
you can ask me what you want.
And they want 2 sacks of rice
Okay, I give them. Now full grown, the elder
male Storm is the patriarch of this
group of rescue tigers. He has been the
key to the other streams of letting
his tiger population grow. Four months
ago, the monastery reach the turning
point, this very first tiger to arrive is
now a proud father of two cubs, one male
and one female. It was the answer to the
abbot streams. In our dreams, or in my
dreams, the sky, every people want to be
in the sky, or in stars or something like this.
It is very difficult for the human to get
the star, you know very diffcultbut. So that's
why he come to me. I just choose,
that one or that one, that one. Some of
the sky or star like this. The
added names of the tigers after the heavens as
he believes they are heaven-sent. He
named the young female Malika meaning
star and her twin brother em far meaning
flying into the sky.
The young female Malika is a
curious, playful new edition. Her good
nature and boundless energy delight the
monks. Very naughty, because they
move very fast. That one, the little one, they move very fast.
If we let them out
we have to catch them in the cage first
Naughty tiger! As time went by, the
Monastery group reputation and more
people brought in cubs whose parents had
been killed by poachers. The forest
temple was unwittingly becoming a tiger
orphanage.
It was never designed to house unwanted
tigers but for the abbot the alternative
is unthinkable.
How can i take them back to the jungle?
He can't stay in the jungle. When they
hungry, they come to see the people, the
people there shoot them. So if I take them back
to the jungle, like I take them
go to their deaths. a virgin pussy never asked for
the tigers to come to him, but now they wait
were here, he was not going to let them
down.
This simple man was about to rewrite the
rules of keeping large predators
alongside humans. The destiny of a bird
Archon posted and his tigers was sealed.
Just four months since she would have
fit into one hand the new cub, Dalika,
is growing up fast.
She's already becoming a force of nature.
She will soon be too big to enjoy a trip
out in the local area, but for now it's
stimulating treat, taking in the sights
and sounds of her world. Dalika's world
is conscience of worried on the border
between Thailand and Burma. Every year
thousands of tourists visit the river
kwai bridge and pay respects to the
fallen allied soldiers who were forced
to build this implmennce Japanese railway.
Margarita Steinhardt is a Russian
scholar who was visiting the wartime
shrines last year when she heard about
the forest temple. When the abbot invited
her to stay, she didn't hesitate. As an
ecologist, she found this the perfect
place to study tigers in close proximity
For the first time, an outsider has been
allowed to witness the relationships
between the tigers on the monks. By the
fact that they grew up here from very
little age, all together with so much
human contact, their wild instincts
haven't been developed at all.
They totally undisturbed by as they
don't us as potential prey or they are
threatened by us. Today, he is sitting
next to me, a tiger almost like a puppy
dog. Sometimes the tigers here seem to
have forgotten that they are tigers at
all. The second of the hill tribe tigers
has bonded with the abbot to such an
extent. He is now the most spoiled tiger
in the canyon.
He still suckles the abbot's thumb,
old habits die hard.
This large predator name Thunder, still
thinks he's a cub, even the small stones
on the pathway causing the problem.
This is one fussy attention seeker.
They grew up with people, most of them
came here just a few weeks old, and they are
hand raised by people, so they look at us
as, not all of us, the monks particularly
as almost mother figures. He makes like he's
friendly like this, he come to me, like he wants to say something.
He want to say happy, or he wants to say hello or something
something you want to
say happy all we. Wants to
speak with me like this, want to
speak. The abbot is like a proud
parent to his tigers. His favorite Storm,
one of the first two tigers to arrive, is
not as gentle as his brother dainty
brother. His crooked tail is testament to
his earlier brutal mistreatment at the
hands of the poachers.
He's like a son to the abbot, all be it,
an unruly teenager. The first tiger here
and that one. So now he thinks he's
the boss. So he can control every
tiger here, this one. The monks have
to be a certain kind of person to handle
their oversized cats. Each of the abbot
disciples are here for different reasons.
Monk Pu is the most enthusiastic of the
monks. He has taken charge of the video
camera donated to the monastery by a
wealthy follower, and is compiling a
unique video diary of the temple tigers.
Getting this close to a full-grown tiger,
is very dangerous but who will able to get
closer than any other as, he's known many
of the tigers since they were cubs. They
trust him and it returned pose happily
for home movies of breathtaking intimacy.
I love them a lot, especially these two new born cubs
Hern Fa, and Dalika
because I fed them with milk,
bathed them and took care of them.
There is one monk who knows no
fear.
Monk June can handle all of the tigers
without flinching, he can overcome their
aggression and this fascinates him. As a monk
I like it because I have never seen
a tiger. After I see them I want to be close to them.
To know what it will be like because the
tiger is a fierce animal. It is a delicate
balancing act, once a tiger intimidate
some monk, people forever assume
dominance. You would not want to fill
ground tiger to think it was above you
in their social pecking order.
The monks enter this minefield with
nothing in their armoury, accept a stick,
a bottle of water and a lot of nerve.
A monk do have sticks and the tiger is
actually conditioned to respond to erase
hand with a stick in hand and water.
They do back out, every
time I've seen a tiger misbehave,
Monk will approach the tiger wood back
off a hundred percent, but these are
animals, they act on instincts,
anything can happen really. Sometimes it
turns into a battle of wills. Normally
practice Storm is getting irritated in the
canyon.
Usually it's a simple matter of saving
face,
unfortunately for Storms neighbor
someone had to take the hit.
Yes I got bitten but it's not so hard.
After bitting they just release.
They are just teasing.
You have to be with them a longer period
If they are with you for only 2 or 3 days,
they may really bite you. There's one guest here
who takes up the most manpower. He's a Bengal tiger
and a big one at that.
The abbot calls him Mac meaning cloud.
Almost two metres long and weighing in
a 250 kilos, he dwarfs his smaller
Indo-Chinese cousins, and he knows it. A
little bit of trouble from character
probably due to his size, he's dominating
the others tiger, I guess and he could be difficult
to control due to the strength he has. He
arrived here when he was four or five
months old so here still retain some of
these wild instinct. He is not as tame as
the others.
I'll make he's biggest tiger
here. He's good and Maek is strong
andhe scare all of the tigers.
A fearless individual who cannot be
intimidated.
There is of course only one monk who can
handle him. The monk here cried room, he
seems to have the best relationship with
Mac, some say they even have similar
temperaments, similar personalities. He
has recently started to form an intense
rivalry with the other male tiger Storm.
Even with the Phillies monk June to keep
nor and order in the canyon, the abbot
one more monks to be at the ready in
case they fight each other for dominance.
For now the mighty Mac must remain the cage.
There is one tiger who is so popular,
she is seldom in her cage. The playful
cub young Dalika is now getting too big
to chase piglets. Today she is the
picture of health but she very nearly
died. At birth,
her mother rejected her and as a result
of the constant handling of humans, are
delicate hip became disticated. She
was to prove that raising tiger is no
easy thing. Dalika.
The abbot went to Dr. Somechai
Visasmonkolchai for advice on what to do
with the first cub. He is in fact used to
treating horses and cattle not sickly
tiger cubs. He had to learn from scratch.
Okay this is the first cups that was born in
captivity here.
So their mother not accept and
we separate them from the mother and
then take care of them. And at the first step
she cannot eat, so we change the
nutrition. Now se can eat about 5 kilograms
per day so it's quite good, a little bit
fatter.
With the right nutritional, the cubs are
now growing stronger and cheekier. But it's
all trial and error, there are no
presidence for looking after wild tigers
in a  Buddhist monastery. They seem to be
doing everything quite perfectly. There is
nothing that stands out to be wrong with
the place.
I've observed for myself how the cubs
grow up, how they develop at what age,
which things  happen to them.
I’ve looked into their behaviour but I have
a lot of data which I haven't
analysed yet and I will have to do a
comparative study with  zoo tigers and
I’ll see the differences in behavior.
Through the experience of Dalica, the
monks now know much more about raising
tiger cubs. It's a good thing.
Six days ago two more cubs were born.
The  monastery is now full. For the
moment, these are the last cubs that can
be born here.
This makes them very special indeed. The
adult has named the growing cubs Fa Mai
meaning new day and Fa Rong meaning
sunshine. As the weeks pass, mongpus
video diary records the progress of the
new cubs.
I didn't have get married yet. I didn't have
because  I am a pico. But your wife
have  pregnant something like that.
Yeah, in the area I feel happy like this.
So, I feel like that
like all baby come here and come to me. As
his family of predators grows, the adult
knows that he cannot continue his work
with the tigers unless the
infrastructure of the  monastery changes.
He is hatching a remarkable and
ambitious plan.
To create more space  for his charges, Kanchanaburi
has planned to convert 20
acres of land behind the cages  into a
natural  forest playground for his tigers.
Come here, here.
From here, we plan the new house for them. If
the  tiger is one, the next generation, the next generation
and the next generation. The  project are
planning to take them back to the jungle.
that's all of my dream. Many would think of it
as an impossible dream for a handful of
monks living in a remote  forest. But our
champusit does not know the meaning of
impossible.
His determination and spirit has
attracted followers from all walks of
life, teachers, lawyers and rather
usefully a local Thai army general.
These Thai soldiers are used to taking
orders  but today their orders will not
come from any army officer.
The forest land will be clear to form a
trench six meters deep and eight meters
wide.
This will be the safety boat encircling
a central area behind the existing
gauges forming a tiger island.
There is much work ahead but achampus
dream is starting to become a
reality. For the  monks, it's a rare
opportunity to escape the confines of
the  monastery and head out. They want to
take a look at a tiger breeding reserve
70 kilometers to the North. Aaway from the
watchful eyes of the  Abbott, who is to
know if they're single rice meal of the
day is supplemented by something  little
tastier. This sanctuary has been set up
by the Thai government for homeless and
confiscated tigers. They are deliberately
left alone with minimal human contact.
magic part 104 another copy number    not
done yet
Danielle    and    I have another    landing    how
I    will die
These aren't the tim  tigers of the
monastery but they still recognize the
monks tiger calls.
The tiger island will feature a similar
compound surrounded by a fence. Back for
another    great. Satisfaction all-round.
Soon monk June will see his tigers
roaming as free as the ones here,  but
their exuberance  is going to be
short-lived. Back home    a dark cloud hangs
over the  monastery, one of the abbot's
cubs has died.
The  monastery is having a black day. The
digging had stopped and the soldiers have
returned to bar rest.  Beneath the soft
red earth,  detractors    have    hit    hard
bedrock that will have to be cleared
before  doing can continue but the money
has run out.
It's a huge disappointment. Half of the
way is very difficult  work to do,
because when we dig, we have a
problem  with the stone like this.
We have to dig 8m length and deep about 6m.
And in 6m, we have a lot of rock
like this. So very difficult, half way
to do now. We we need about 10 10
million Baht.
I think should be enough for digging. If
the digging is not completed before the
rainy season,  the sides will collapse and
the land will return to  forest. it's bad
news that the monastery has much worse to
follow. Both of the new cubs contracted
bronchitis,  the weaker of the twins
Sunshine has died.
Her brother  Newday has managed to scrape
through,  but the abbot is extremely
worried that he might suffer a relapse.
Much to his frustration, he now has to
endure a frequent checkups at the vets
clinic in the village.
Ihe infection is bacteria acute
infection, is very, very rapid and very
fast. So it has high temperature, cannot
eat, cannot drink and no sound and this
is the serious case and he says there
was die and Fa Mai is good luck. At his
evening retreat,  the abbot meditates with
a heavy heart. The loss of young Sunshine
is devastating, but Kanchanaburi sits
world is within the bigger picture of
life and existence.
The Abbot is a Buddhism monk, basically he
believes in reincarnation.  He told a lot
that  not just only the tigers in the
forest temple, but all the wild animals
in the  forest temple is used to be the
monks, used to be their family, used to be
their friend.
We dig the hole and put them in the
ground before they leave. Okay,
so if you want to
come back, please come back and stay with
me.
On their daily ride into town to beg
for Bahts, the mood in the truck is somber.
The monks just lost a much-loved tiger
cub and the tiger Island project is in
jeopardy. But life goes on, the monks do
not deal with money and so cannot buy
themselves any food, they have to accept
whatever the local people can spare for
them. The needs of the monks and the
needs of the tigers run in tenden with
the forest temple. A monastic life means
a monastic diet eating red meat would go
against Buddhist belief, so how contend
meat-eating tigers live a Buddhist life?
Each morning, the monks walk to the
village to receive vegetarian food  and
rice from the locals. The tigers are fed
with chicken bones carefully minced to
take away the appearance of meat. Then,
dog biscuits are added. Everything is
cooked and monks make sure that there
are no traces or any hints of blood.
The  tigers are not quite vegetarians as
the monks are but they do not see this
food  as the meat of another living being.
It is a Buddhist principle but it seems
to also be good science. If tigers would
taste blood,
it might or might not awaken their wild
instincts. But then if a person  plays
with the  tiger and gets bitten or cut
and then the tiger tastes blood. It will
straightaway associated with food.
Both tigers and monks eat only
one meal a day, it is an occasion to be
savoured. Dalica and her brother are the
privileged ones, sitting at the  monks
table  .
life is a monk is a precarious existence,
they live on donated meals, donated land
dressed in donated robes and feed the
tigers with donated food.
It all comes from  the local community.
Leftovers are given to the other animals,
it's all about giving.
It's customary for the local people to
buy an animal like a chicken or even a
buffalo from a slaughterhouse to then
set it free at a temple. In doing so, they
have saved  a life which they believe
helps them in the next reincarnation.
Today, the  monastery is about to get a
new  addition. The village heads
grandchildren have found a baby deer
while they were playing in the forest
The tiny mouse deer is lost after being
abandoned by its mother.
The excited young followers insist on
presenting it to the averred earthling.
Recently, the abbot lost a life. Now a new
tiny life has found its way to the
forest temple. A gift from the local
people,  the circle of life and death is
complete.
The  tigers are in town.
To the local people,
Dalica a new day are a welcome sight on
their weekly food trip  at the town.
These local  villagers give their full
support to the abbot, happy to see his
tigers whenever they came
and by their presence in the local
community, the tigers are giving
something back. Riding  on the tiger
temple reputation, a foundation has been
setup, staffed by volunteers to help the
poor communities in the area. The
monastery grounds are now home to a small
radio station which reaches out
educating the people on the wrongs of
poaching  as well as the abbot buddhist
teachings of kindness and compassion.
indoor techies subsidies
the   museum. It has created a loyal
following of supporters to a keen to see
his plans for a tiger  island become a
reality. The villagers seem to
understand how important the  wild
animals to daily lives and they stopped
hurting  the animals. It means we
concern a big group of animal lover.
The big group of animal lover is more
valuable for conservation  because if we
realise that we  had one kinds of
living thing the same as the tiger. So
the tiger has the right to stay on
this earth like ours.
The Katin, one of the biggest
fundraising  festivals in Thai Buddhism.
The Health Ministry comes to life
as usual the tiger cubs Newday and
Dalica about of the festivities.
This year the abbot loyal supporters
have arrived in huge numbers to give the
monastery the begging it desperately
needs. Right now, the tiger project needs
money.
The local people don't disappoint.
It looks like as the Tigers are to get
their  forest playground after all.
There is one  tiger who will particularly
relish the chance to roam the tiger
island. Mac, the huge Bengal tiger is
still cooling off behind bars. If it
wasn't for his hot temper  he would be
going out into the canyon with the
others.  With many monks busy with the
festivities,
there aren't  enough people to control
him. His rival, Storm is not a
particularly brave tiger. If he runs at
the  site of water,
he doesn't stand much chance against the
much stronger force of nature.
Maek, maek  to be everyday if we have the pico is enough
is enough for our look
after them. Then we can let them free.
All of them, all of them out for exercise.
But now is a not many people. For now, Storm
is still the king of the canyon, but not
for much longer
the Averty  wants all his tigers to be
together in the canyon soon.  What the
Averty is lacking in  monks he is more
than making up for in visitors  since the
start of the tiger island project. News
of this monastery and its tigers have
been spreading far and wide.  The
monastery is slowly becoming another in
Thailand mini animal attractions. It is
unexpected but for the abbot it maybe
the Lifeline he needs for his tigers.
Because he eats 1000 Baht a day, all of
them. So we are Buddhist, we  can't we can't
have any money, just  donation from the
tourists and the money they can buy the
food for the boar, white boar for buffalo
and for every animal to come here to eat.
In the future,  I believe that the areas
around will change because more
tourists come. You know some business will
happen. Kanchanaburi used to be a
tourist spot in terms of the  River Kwai,
and the train, the bridge like that.
like that, that's very sad, a
tragedy history. But now the new spot
here, very joyful. When they came here to
see, they will be happy with the
tranquil environment.
The tourists are not the only ones
enjoying the peace and tranquility, the
mother of the cubs, Sunta One, meaning some
being, is out again for the first time
since giving birth. She is frisky today,
excited to have the chance to show her
affection towards her mate, Storm. They
have two sets of cubs together now, but
the  abbot hopes they will have more.
Their mutual adoration is almost human.
Storm is dominant to the canyon, but only
because one of the abbot tigers    is
still missing.
Maybe tomorrow we can bring him out.
But he’s on heat now. There
are  now enough monks to handle Mac if
things get ugly with Storm.  The two
tigers  are finally to get their showdown.
The  Army is back, the tiger island is
starting to take shape.  The huge boulders
are no match for the newly purchased
explosives. In order to preserve the
tigers existence here,  their old way of
life will be consigned to history.  Each
load of  Earth removed brings the tigers
one step closer to a new life under the
guise of visiting tourists. The abbot is
unwittingly adding a new attraction to
the long list of  wildlife destinations
in  Thailand.
This is  Tiger Tourism in Thailand, just
to our South of the capital Bangkok.
Tourists gather to indulge their
fascination with the  danger and beauty of
the big cats. Here  tigers entertain the crowds
with tricks.  They are healthy animals but
they must work for a living.
They must attract the crowds.
People come here and there curious  to
see newborn tiger cubs suckling a pig. The
mother tigress is giving the piglets the care
for. It is a curious spectacle that draws
people from near and far.  How is the
monastery and its tigers going to find a
place in these existing frameworks of
tiger tourism. Now we have no policy to
be a zoo.
It cannot be like that, it depends on the
management, making a system.
So we need support from experienced
and skilled person to help us manage this
this thing.
They are in  unchartered territory, there
is simply no where else to draw a
comparison. It is going to be a delicate
balancing act between the spirit of the
monastery and the demands of commercial
tourism. In the company of his beloved
tigers, Anchanaburi has a lot to
ponder on his  favourite  trip of the week
to watch the young tigers play in the
cool waters of the River Kwai.
And knowingly they are playing on the
foundations of the long destroyed
wartime River Kwai Bridge. The amateurs
promised himself that his tigers will
become an inspiration for this area. From
the remnants of such sorrow, he is trying
to build up a new sense of happiness
and  a love for all living things.
That is all in the future, for today
there is one last promise for the abbot
to  fulfil. The monks are about to tackle
something more volatile  and gunpowder.
The 250 kilograms male tiger Mac, the
abbot finally has enough manpower to
bring him out. On his arrival of the
Canyon, he tries again to assert his
dominance. All stand aside to let him
have the pool to himself, but the old
score with Storm still needs to be
settled.
In the wild, they would fight to the
death, but here neither tiger gets
hurt in this exchange. It's play-acting
under the abbots come control, all animals
here  coexist in peaceful harmony.
This place is doing an incredible job.
They never intended this place to be a
zoo to keep tigers to benefit themselves
or anyone else for that matter. They
rescued the animals. They're playful,
they're happy, they're  mating, which is a
great sign and if they manage to find
some professional help that there is a
great potential as a rehabilitation
center.
Watchanhuset can finally see his dreams
coming true.
This simple man has pursued untried and
untested principles of raising wild
predators and seems to be making it work.
Conservationists in the  West may not
recognize these as accepted methods of
raising tigers. This is Eastern
conservation. The Western conservation
maybe they think just only wild
should be wild.
Okay. Wild cannot turn to be like tame or too
close to the human being.
Eastern Conservation, it means
happiness. Whenever you see the tiger
happy, that it mean just successful in
conservation.
And with his faith in the goodness and
compassion of human nature, this
remarkable man will not rest until his
tigers are finally living in peace.  All
of human being in the world, we can stay
in the peace, not fighting in the
war. Like my friend, my father, my mother
and  everything and every every people
and every animal here, we have the same
blood, the blood is red. When you
take, it’s red. We are the same blood.
We just different about the
species, that's all.