Outback Australia,
an unforgiving territory and a land of
amazing creatures,
where sometimes nature needs a helping
hand.
These are the everyday heroes found by a
single mission to save wildlife anywhere
anytime.
In this episode of outback wildlife
rescue, took his care back three months ago.
Will Archimedes the koala ever return
to the wild?
He’s not even trying to fight us off. The
ways to save this need cut.
I don't know how anyone could do this to. The
big one you can see it there and over here.
And an uninvited guest who refuses to
leave the dinner table.
It's like a restaurant, an the outback
restaurant for these guys.
Australia is a massive continent, from
the tropical Queensland Aoast to what's
called the top-end, Darwin.
At the monsoonal wetlands that surround
and South
through the arid interior to the red
deserts of Alice Springs and field.
An hour up the Queensland Coast from
Brisbane,
there's a vet clinic like no other, the
Australian wildlife hospital and be a
while. They’re lining up in the doorway now. All
the sealed the cages that are starting to
appear. The day begins.
It's a non-stop 24-hour mash-up
clinic. Next,
I think I've got more flying foxes. Ah, think
I've got possibly a kangaroo and that's a
whole stack of birds waiting as well, so
planning to do for the next few hours.
Everyday they get called to help
hundred or more rescued creatures and
they’re queuing up from the crack of dawn.
Lots of our animals because they're nocturnal
get it the night before and they found
during the early hours, the mornings. So,
most mornings tend to be like this. We’ll
busy out. Gail Gipp manages the hospital.
John Hangers, the senior vet. Still
feel it a bit of moment. They're hardened to the fact that
more than two-thirds of the animals
brought here have either been hit by a
car or attacked by a family dog. Dog
attack
injuries are toriously hard to fix
because they often have very severe
internal injuries
so they're hard to. You know they're
challenging patient to get through any
way. We probably saved on our own ,maybe
fifty percent of them.
A quarter of the patients are koalas
and this morning has been a bad one for
them. Its got a fracture her, right? Actually, I
have call
this rounded.
Despite their looks, koalas aren't bears,
they're marsupials,
uniquely adapted for Australian life.
Their front paws each have two thumbs to
help them climb and inside there's an
organ like an appendix 2 meters long to
help digest the tough eucalyptus leaves
they ate.
Of course what they can't do is adapt to
people
in between cars and habitat loss some
estimate their population to be as low
as 100,000.
It's fun
at the moment, it’s a car hitch. She was hit at
seven o'clock this morning.
We unsure the extent of their injuries at
the moment up and that she's in a lot of
pain and just got quite a swollen face.
One end is working on
was hit last night.
She's gotten internal
damage and isn't it also in a lot of
pain.
And the one in there is a boy that came in
yesterday that has spinal injuries.
Each of these koalas faces a long
difficult road to recovery. Be great.
It's a journey Archimedes is all too
familiar with. Three months ago his life
hung in the balance on an operating
table too, but everyone's hoping today
he'll get the all-clear to return to the
world.
Katherine lies 300 kilometers south of
Darwin,
in the northern territory.
Ten thousand people trading the border
between the desert and the tropics and
one of them is on a wildlife rescue
mission.
We've just received a call from a lady
on the other side of town who has a big
snake she says it’s in a chock pain. So, I will
hit there straight away and hopefully save
her and the snake.
David Reed really is his name calling has
the government contract to rescue
wildlife here about. He answers 500 calls
out every year, all at the ripe old age
of 21.
It was what I was born to do, it’s my ideal
job, it’s my ideal passion and I just
consider myself so lucky to be able to
do what I did.
So for really, this is a labor of love.
Every rescue is a chance to save an
animal and help a human. Morning, how are you?
I’m good. How are you? Thanks for coming
out so quick. That’s alright. Aren’t you say
you got another snake? Did you?
It is great and it has greet us already
Oh well looked after you got time for it.
Absolutely. Where has he been hiding?
He’s up in the corner where there’s a
bag and roasters are there as they use to do.
they're all in there still
Reeding choking now but he's going to
have his hands full
Steven Carter and Lisa Handsome run Darwin’s
Ark Animal Hospital.
When it comes to injured wildlife that's
a more than must around here but by
the side of the road
they've stumbled onto one of the most
shocking scenes either of them have ever
encountered. Had to believe but we've
just come across this kite here.
He wasn't easy to spot is just right
down the riverbank. Some horrible person
has made a snared trap bed and it swayed.
It's just been hanging by one wing and tell
how long. Long enough. Look
there’s no leaves around like here. So, it’s been here for
a while. It’s been in this state for a while.
He's not even he's not even trying to
fight us off. He is covered in ants is just
poor thing at and I don't know how
anyone could do this to. It's a whistling
kite, a bird of prey common across
main land Australia.
This was young and didn't know enough to
avoid the snare. Lisa and Stephen are his
only hope.
He's just a baby he haven't greet
welcome to the world. Can I take you out?
You can see. Yes it’s swollen.
Poor sweet heart. at the moment it's
really swollen.
say there's certainly not going to be a
lot of soft tissue damage and possibly
even some permanent damage to the blood
supply
that destroy the trap. We don't want
anyone else getting caught in it.
See people putting them in a trap.
I can't believe it.
Let's have a look at the swing can have
to make sure we get all the cotton off
because it's going to act like a ton
of cocaine and became the blood supply
off to the end of the wing is
undoubtedly quite dehydrated and a fair
degree of shock and he's giving up.
You can see here so the placides and
we really need to get him back to the
clinic.
Thank you.
In Katherine, Reed is moving in to
tackle what’s apparently a very big snake
in Marylyn's henhouse. Snakes
you know in Katherine are a particular
favorite animal and a lot of people are
still scared of them.
So you're trying to save the snake and
you know save the people at the same
time. The snake can get in but then he
has a meal and has a trouble getting
back  out. The large lump. So he'll
find a nice shady spot, kill out there
and try to digest food on the days.
He certainly is a big one you can see it
there and over here.
It's an olive python which can grow more
than four meters long.
They're not venomous and kill their
pride by constricting it until it
suffocates.
More often that's wallabies or lizards or
in this case a slow chicken.
He's coming here looking for dinner. He's
found that last night.
People that keep a lot of chucks or
even birds and everything like this.
It's like a restaurant, an outback
restaurant for these guys so it really
is a big attraction and it's not an
uncommon circumstances found among this.
Really has to catch this snake and it's
not to be taken like this. He's not poisonous,
but you can still give a nasty bite.
All right we'll see if we can get him
out and get him away and save some of
the rest of the chucks.
Respect is my golden rule when working
with snakes. Certainly it’s a big snake. He’s
probably going on near three mavis and
he's a little bit defensive you can see
in there. Snakes will very vulnerable at
this sort of time like he's got a rather
large food source in him and he's
sitting there saying that “You know I'm
vulnerable, I can't move this last. That's
what I normally do.
Stay away my long body. So we'll see if
we can pick him up. This nice and easy.
In due while, the operating theatre is still
full of sick koalas. Have sever bash on the
head
And out in the recovery area, Archimedes
is waiting his turn for treatment.
He's had a rough time.
His care about three months ago and he
had a fractured jaw so these are the
x-rays or some of the x-rays of
Archimedes when it came in.
The fracture that he had is a symphyseal
fracture, fracture through the centre of
the jaw.
So that the treatment for, um,
the fractured synthesis just really
involves wiring together the two
in sizes on the lower jaw. It sounds
simple enough, but Archimedes had other
ideas.
He kept breaking those wires. Fractured
jaw fell apart three times on us and we
have to repair it consistently,
so he was touching go for a long time.
Now at long last,
they're hoping his jaw is probably yield,
but they need to check with a final
examination.
That sedative will stop him struggling
and hurting himself.
it's a really big day for Archimedes,
because we didn't think he was gonna
make it back to the wild.
With luck,
by the time he wakes up he'll finally be
ready to go home.
We'll see if we can pick him out this
nice and easy.
Snakes have amazing sensors you can see
him flicking his tongue like that.
The thing it is this to be nice and
gentle and sometime the snake
really doesn't want to hurt you.
And once he feels that you're not a
threat, he's normally quite happy. Just to
try and work yourself away rather than
restricting dividing or trying to hurt you so.
But you can really see that's quite a
large lump and that will probably be a
couple of kilos with food so it probably
might have been the first time that he's
eaten possibly in bed four five
maybe even six months after the dry
season. So we sort of compare the size of
that lump to the size of his head.
They really is quite a huge difference
so it's amazing the muscles that snakes
can use to stretch edge or and allow
them to swallow such big prey. Turns out
Reedies quite the snake charmer but
Marylyn still keeping a distance. If you
live in the territory, you
you have to be prepared to live with
snakes because that's part a lot up here
and it seems if you've got chuck's you
have snakes. Alright, nice and easy into the
bag.
Up here they have a unique way of
measuring big snakes.
He's probably about 15 kilos which is
equivalent to two cases of beer so quite
substantial for Australian snake. The
girls in the henhouse are breathing a big
sigh of relief.
Now the challenge for Reed is to find a
safe place to release the snake.
In Darwin, Stephen and Lisa have brought the
injured whistling kite back to the Ark.
Its feet. Let's have a look at it.
They found him hanging in a trap and
exhausted from the struggle.
Okay. Kites are hunters.
Their site is thousands of times better
than ours.
They'll drop on mice and lizards from
more than a hundred meters up, but this
one won't be doing that for a while.
This guy's been hanging from his wing
and it's very common for them to
break their core bland. That shows a
bit sore, a bit wrench that the anti-inflammatories
should help to let down
make him feel better. I just feel like the
moment for any breaks or fractures
so at the damage is still a lot of
swelling. It doesn't appear to be any
break, so already significant damage
there. We’ll take an x-ray to confirm
that’s all attack. All things considered
the kites in remarkably good shape.
X-ray. With that engine wing,
there's no way he can be set free yet. we
got a training with some
anti-inflammatories and antibiotics and
time. He's going to need some looking
after for a while and Lisa
as a unique halfway house in mind.
In Katherine, Reedies got a whole bag of
olive python to deal with. But for the
time good,
he won't be setting it free just here.
With the olive python that we got this
morning on the call out in chock pain.
We’ll decide to
put him in his top here leaving peace
and quiet,
let him digest his meal without any
stress and we go. You got to remember
this snake again like he's being keep
up nice and tight in the bag, away from
stress, away from any other people and
this order to help him keep quiet. Reedies
handling the python with a lot of care
because right now there's a risk that
chicken dinner could come back up again.
If you stretch it up too much,
one thing they might do is actually
regurgitated and the best thing for the
snake is to actually let him keep that
meal down and digest and get all the
value from it that he can.
So we'll put him here nice and quiet. It
may seem like a small box for a big
snake but within the next week or until
we go. I guess the meal,
he won't be moving a hell of a lot
anyways. He will be quite happy to have a
nice environment where
he can sit down, curl up and not be disturbed.
Archimedes time has finally come be a
while,
he's been anaesthetised for his
examination.
So, how’s it been going to sure? He was hit
by a car and broke his jaw. To tighten
and then.
It's a problem they see almost every day
here at the clinic.
They’re so small. They really bump about
the level for a lot of cars and they
usually come off really badly
which is unfortunate for them.
John can't take any chances if
Archimedes is free too soon. He won't be
able to feed and he die.
Just we're doing that final check before
they release and the warn just to make
sure that we haven’t overlooked
something or they haven't developed
another condition while they been here.
It's basically just a thorough
general physical examination like they
might receive when they when they first
admitted. I think people realise
the states of the koalas and
the realities that they will be gone from
urban areas in
a lifetime,
I think that we are responsible for that,
and we owe them so much.
Every koala released back to the wild
matters
but can Archimedes be set free?
Reedies on his way to release the
troublesome olive python.
He’s digested his stolen chicken and
really knows exactly the right place to
set him free.
Down by the river and away from people.
All pythons love the water. This is
an ideal environment for him, so we'll
let him go, let him adapt into his new
environment and you know hopefully will
be a safe and happy life going to
continue on living away from people. Olive
Pythons in this sort of habitat along
the river corridor would quite often come
across maybe some possums, you know large
birds probably even ducks or something
like that. You know their food source in
the river corridor is abundant,
so that's why it's a good environment to
release a snake especially big you know
olive python which commonly
preys on you know birds or mammals
marsupials. There will be a lead let him
go and hopefully by the time it warms up
a bit later the day. He will have found a
place to you know hard up and sit at the
day then probably come out at night
seeing pythons are nocturnal.
He’ll be nice and happy so not a chuck
pain from are hoping the chucks are safe,
the snake safe and I can all live
happily ever after.
The whistling kites life is on the up,
Lisa and Stephen free him from the snare
and he's largely uninjured. He's had a
lucky escape,
which is ironic given he's about to
become a jail bird.
Very good thanks. For getting new edition
for you are. Just as good as it.
He's a little whistling kite. The
Ark help set up a program at Darwins
Prison where inmates like volunteer
to help injured wildlife.
Hey you can say yeah. This wing here you can
so if you pull out
you can see he got, you can see
how he’s all swollen and he’s looking a
little bit better but not good but if
you compare it to the other wing
it's quite seek. What do you reckon? The
guides pretty much guaranteed 24-hour
care and in just 12 months more than 150
animals have passed through here.
That's really good is actually used both
swings there like that main certainly
hasn't got any significant nerve damage.
So,
he shouldn't be here for too long. Yep,
that's right that's very good sign.
Yeah shouldn't take him too long and
he'll be up and flying around with the
other birds. He’ll used to it.
Yeah, thanks Stanley. Thanks. See you later.
The kite’s journey wont’ end here,
provided all goes well.
Lisa will be back to spring him in a
month.
This is another good day we've managed
to rescue this little bird and send him
up here and I've seen him fly. I know he's
going to be ready for release.
It's just a fantastic day, it’s a good day.
And it's a good day in via too.
Archimedes has passed his physical,
he's almost time.
Koalas a territorial little creatures.
Kate from the release team is putting
Archimedes back near the old haunt where
it was found.
He's ready to go that’s for sure.
Hey buddy.
That’s him calling.
Getting back to his territory is letting
everyone know he’s home and he's a young
man so he's going to give a party
tonight I don't know. But he’s certainly happy to
be back.
Flay gums is one of their favourite food
sources, so he's gonna
have plenty to eat here forever. It’s great.
Archimedes releases one small victory in
the battle to help a species survive.
Young and healthy,
he could breed for the next 10 years so
hopefully this little woman could make a
big difference.
That's a baby,
that's a lot,
it's just a little animal.
To be out to release it that to show you
that you doing your job well.
It’s fantastic. The best feeling on this
planet I think.
I love it