She's got one. Tigers are generally
said to succeed just one time out of
10, but this tiger kills on average
every third try.
She needs to be good. Her cubs have
already got huge appetites
and by the time they leave her, they will weigh
eight times as much.
Even at this size,
each cub consumes around two kilos of meet
at a single sitting.
The camera elephants take a bath
every day. They work for five hours at a
stretch
then the rest of the day is that round.
In the sweltering summer, this daily
ritual brings much needed relief
from the heat. The cubs
also like a cooling dip but the pool by
the den
is not large, and when their mother joins
in, things can get a little crowded.
In spite of the heat,
summer is a good time of year for some of the
forest animals.
These are
among the rarest sloth
bears. They only venture out during the
day in the most secluded places
but spy cam was there to record them.
They are feasting
on formal food.
Wild boar
also partial to food. Most animals fear
sloth bears as but not apparently wild
boar, at least not in this food around.
Although that is pain for all,
it is sometimes necessary for the bears
to show who is boss. The bear cubs
are walking out where they stand in the
pecking order,
they are aggressive creatures by nature and
will face down even the biggest
predators,
but they must show no fear.
Even so, for the youngsters, things sometimes get
just too much
and it's time to retreat. The tigers
have moved from their small and shrinking
bathtub
to a more commodious bathing pool,
a reservoir
built by the local people to provide
some with water throughout the year.
It's a great place to cool down. The
sambar deers
are feeling the heat too.
The wild boars
also enjoy a mud bath and combining the
wallow with the meal
just doubles the pleasure.
Mud bathing is clearly enjoyable
but it also helps animals get rid of
ticks and other skin parasites.
The tigers
have yet found the perfect spot. Cubs
are off the shade. Tigers
are one of the few cats that actually
enjoy swimming
and they usually pick den sites close to
water. As they travel around the
territories during the summer,
they move as quickly as possible through
the dryer parts
to get to the hunting grounds that would
have bathing places.
As June comes to an end, the heat becomes
really hard to bear.
Midday temperatures can reach 45 degrees
in the shade,
but after a bath the water
evaporating from the fur cools the
body and brings enough relief
for the animal to sleep with. When the monsoon
finally
arrives, it's not moment too soon
As weather has been bringing a welcome drop in
temperature
the rain replenish the ponds, puddle and pools.
There is greenery everywhere.
The giant to me to WebDAV golden all
spiders hand between trees.
There are the biggest spiders' webs in the
world,
national concurring ropes sometimes
scratch across
six meter gaps. The elephant are
about to march through them. The
spiders themselves
have a span as wide as a human hand but
today are of no consequence to an elephant.
Their web
is strong enough to catch a small bird
but the spiders in fact feed only
on insects. Cubs
are just over a year old and they have
an appetite
to match their size, but there has been
a significant change in their behavior.
Their play
now includes mock hunting with mother
serving as a target.
This is a stylized fighting. It looks
dangerous and aggressive but the cubs keep
their paws
fully throughout. Mother
never takes part in their fighting games
but indulgently
tolerates the cubs' boisterous behavior.
They spend a lot of time traveling. Five
nearly full size tigers on the move
together is a rare sight indeed.
They are a formidable force, nothing
stays around
to challenge them.
Even the weather is now cooler, they still
bath
on the hottest part of the day. Water is
difficult to resist.
The cubs take new notice whatever at the
elephants,
so it's possible to get really into a
chaos from the camera Helton
truck.
Progress through the forest is slow because
they link at
almost every pool allstream.
They're not alone in relishing the abundance of water.
The langur monkeys and their
babies seem to have not to care in the
world,
but for some babies drinking isn't the
most comfortable of
times.
Unlike mechanics, langurs are the friends
of spotted deer.
They share the task of keeping a lookout
for their greatest enemy.
The time has come for the tigers to make
a determined hunt.
One of her cubs decides to go with her to
get some
personal tuition,
the rest prefer to take it easy.
They are now starting to behaviors
individuals, each making its own
decisions about what each
do.
The tigers doesn't need to look far for
a meal, she's in one of the most
productive parts of trees.
She hasn't been here for some time
so she has more chance of catching a
pray of god.
The lush
undergrowth gives her a cover.
Her pray she quite i'm concerned.
But not for long the cup
still to learn that this sort of
behaviour is not what is needed
when mother is trying to hunt. The langur
send a warning far and wide,
but still
the cub doesn't calm down. The cub
is now testing his mother's patience to
the limit. She warns him
that enough is enough.
The rest of the cubs
are contained to wait and two cheese
course something
that shows just how well fed they are.
Her prey soon relax the pools
are beginning to dry.