Over the breeding enclosure, everything
is set the introduction of Nina and
amiga. I'm going to be going into the
enclosure myself. I'm going to take a
little not to protect myself, but just in
case there is any adverse reaction
between the two cats, so I need a broom
just to stop surprising that if we do
get her reaction. Snow leopards are
powerful predators that can inflict
serious harm on each other and us. Other
collections would never dream of
entering a big cat enclosure like this
during an introduction, but Terry trust
his cats and takes everything in stride,
a risky business. With Nina still
snoozing on top of the platform, it's up
to amiga to come out and introduce
herself.
It's not usual in the wild for female
snow leopards to share territory and
Nina's instincts are kicking in.
Submissive Amiga doesn't want to fight,
and goes to see what you can find out about
this new unfriendly housemate. All she is
doing is checking out the smells from
Nina, the beauty of Atlas, is that because
Nina worse when she's urinated and
dedicated in here,
she hasn't been under stress so those
one contained threatening smiles, they
pheromones, they produce can indicate to
another cat whether the cat is aggressive
or not, so she's picking out the play
this isn't an aggressive cat so you
know how cats have another approach and
see if we can be friends.
But Nina is on the way down to see Amiga.
Amiga by rubbing up against the walls
and showing Mina her head is displaying
submissive behavior.
With Nina's back turn Amiga sees an
opportunity to get our own back, it will
take time for them to work out each
other's boundaries. Amiga is quite happy to
be friends,
she's just wanting to get close to
show that she's not. While everyone is on
tenterhooks, Terry is the coolest cat
around even taken time out to answer his
mobile phone. As Amiga walks away,
Nina is still wound up
and turns her attention to the other
strangers Mary closure, us.
We have nothing to worry about, we are
protected by terry's trustee brune,
and Nina soon turns our attention back
to Amiga. It may take time for Nina to
fully accept Amiga as her housemate but
once they are coupled with each other
they'll be introduced to an unrelated
male in the hope that at least one of
them will make a produce cubs, as the
day ends it's difficult to forget that
so recently we lost Terbes and her cubs,
something Terry will take time to overcomes.
Next time, family Feud around the dinner
table.
Terry goes in a rare unusual road trip
and time to meet the man of the moment.
I'm Adrian kale I'm a wildlife filmmaker
I've spent years traveling the globe,
filming some of the world's most
fascinating creatures, but right now I'm
just a stone's throw from London England
and here in this leafy paradise
I've discovered something quite
extraordinary. Just behind this
nonchalant looking farm shop is
something that is very un-English. A
secret world of snow leopards,
and lots of them. Behind you Terry!
Dr. Terry More runs the cat
survival trust,
a haven for all cats and home to one of
the biggest collections of snow leopards
on the planet. With snow leopard numbers
falling rapidly in the wild,
each one of these endangered cats here
is special and each birth precious. Come
with me and meet the snow leopards of leafy london!
The farm shop is already opened for
business and customers are starting to
unaware of the WildWorld are waking up
before them.
No two days here at the trust are the
same. Today is no exception
I've only just arrived, Terry's already
taken a call that may well provide a
free meal for the cats.
The local police have found a good
idea for us so we're gonna have to drop
everything and go and pick up another
deer. Something that happens quite
frequently,
fortunately because our cats do love
deer. There we are! There it is. Of course they
have hided it well! That's good
Let's load it up. It's not common for
the local authorities to contact Terry
when animals hit by cars are left on the
roadside. Oh boys!
Terry's cleanup service removed the risk
of further accidents and offers a
natural recycling solution in the
process.
Back at the trust, Robert prepares the
cat food in a very maturafly way.
Firstly i'm going to take the four legs
off, the fore legs and the behind legs.
Behind legs are really good by has
lots of meat when I thought a region. Once that's
done I'm going to take the neck off.
While Rob is going about his business as
the master butcher, the smell coming off
that carcass is quite repulsive and I'm
sure the cats can smell it because
I certainly can. I have left Rob to his
glory task so all getting a bit gruesome
and I've come up here to check in on
Amiga and Nina. Now the two female snow
leopards were recently introduced to
each other and I thought I'd see that
they're playing nicely.
Things are looking very peaceful in the
girls enclosure, Amiga appears to be fast
asleep on the platform,
while Nina is down below in the grass,
rubbing her head against the wall mean
she is still busy scent marking the area.
As part of the trust snow leopard
breeding project, both females have been
put together in preparation for the next
breeding season. By scent marking, Nina is
making Amiga aware of her presence. They
are being given time to get to know each
other first, before meeting a new
breeding male. Up above, Amiga sleep is
disturbed by the sounds of a snow
leopard calling.
Nina recognizes the call and becomes
agitated.
It's Kamal, her father from whom she was
recently separated.
Solitaire and secretive in awhile, snow
leopards generally only call in the
breeding season to try too mate, but this
is not the mating season.
It appears to simply be that Nina and
her dad are communicating.
As the calling subsides, Amiga has moved
down below and is taken a water incorporation
for round two of getting to
know the very vocal Nina. With one of the
largest collection of snow leopards in
the world here at the trust, they become
the main focus of Terry's work but this
is a sanctuary for all cats and the two
female pumas here,
KitKat and crunchy, are a major part of
the family. They're missing a man. So
today I'm heading to explore with Terry,
to remedy the situation. A female puma at
Exmoor zoo in Devon, gave birth to
triplets six months ago. The Cat Survival
Trust has been carefully chosen to adopt
one of the triplets to pair up and
hopefully breathe with their two females.
It is vital for all zoos that the
captive population is kept genetically
healthy.
Thankfully for Terry, Kitkat and Crunchy are an
ideal match for the young male. On
arriving at the zoo,
Danny Reynolds the curator it's Terry
with a bombshell. They don't actually
know for sure that the young puma is a
male. We have sex them three times now, we
still think is three boys the shear rate
at which they just suddenly start to
grow their first the size of their
mother now. Although there's no
development in the normal area would
expect that big animals are quite
came to begin the placement of them.
Completely unfazed by the idea that the
Pumas sex is not yet confirmed.
Terry has just came to meet the young
cat.
But has to wait patiently, as Danny and
his zookeepers collect him from his
enclosure. A good 20 minutes later, cat
box is full and Terry is introduced to
his new family member. In his excitement,
you may have just missed the fact that
the zoo didn't confirm the Pumas sex.
How do you feel? Very happy.
What does he just know? He looks like a
really nice the young puma. After loading
this unnamed puma into the van,
it's straight back onto the road and
back to the trust. A quick break in
the journey allows me to introduce
myself to the latest addition to Terry's
cat family.
He's already referred to the pumas a
male, so who might be otherwise? My
first chance to get a real close look at
the young lad. He is doing well!
He's calm very collected, very composed,
not aggressive with me being here and
just looks beautiful six months old.
You can see big ears, big paws, bit of
grown up to, bit of a body to grow into
their, but the calm cat!
As we arrive back at the trust, there's
no rest as the young puma is carried
through to his new accommodation. You can
probably tell my face that i'm somewhat
happy. We got our potential male.
Potential male now. He's all arrived safe
and sound which is kind to introduce him
to his new quarters. Up until this point,
the puma has had no actual contact with
humans as Exmoor is a non-contact zoo.
Open the box and standing behind it
therefore might appear for hardy but
Terry is keen to start a relationship
with this beautiful cat as soon as
possible.
And of course
this means that the broom comes out to
play.
This is actually quite difficult
situation because he's technically
cornered and he's going to come this way
in order to get into the inside quarters.
This is dangerous, the puma is a wild
animal, nervous and in a strange
environment. Calm as ever,
Terry has a plan involving a bit of wood
and his trusty broom. He believes that by
growing this wildcat, it will calm him,
create a bond and ultimately build a
trust between the two. In a short space
of time, something remarkable
happened.
It's alright. And Terry reminded
me, just how extraordinary his
relationship is, with cats. Just find a
shadow
Okay good. Okay puma forward. It's been
a jam-packed day but what a beauty that
young pumas is. Rob's completed
butchering his deer, now apparently snow
leopard love a nice bit of venison so
he's put it to one side and he's gonna
feed it to the twins and Tammy tomorrow.