Further along the shoreline, Thompson's gazelles
and flamingos xxx drop in. Most elands
had for shade.
A giraffe skip up for some reason in this cesarean sanctuary by the lake
at the end of the corridor.
As seen the leave baboon heading a veritable
army on their wide-ranging quest but anything edible.
Which is most things
They're frightened of leopards and take evasive action.
Don't they know leopards can climb but they soon
back on lands and now for a really nice surprise
the female giraffe who's made we say died in Hell's Gate
and fed the vultures has given birth here in this sanctuary.
cesarean but there seems to be a problem.
It's a mystery why the mother is rejecting the care.
Her milk is crucial to their survival.
The birth cord is still there.
It doesn't look good
There's a distraction some lively warthogs
zebra and some impalas.
A sad loss but that's how nature can be
reality.
But life goes on, the male impala is checking his harem.
It is young ones as they all set off from the safety of the lake
back up the silent corridor. The augur buzzard from his vantage point above
the lake
watches the pelicans move on across the trees searching for more water.
Done there the giraffes are also moving
Could our female to be getting some attention after her loss?
The recent
rain has produced all sorts of new food in the very green grows.
Flowers like decorate being hedges, a prickly pear,
a reminder that the animals on the move or about
to meet people again. But the people
being on a journey doesn't deter them.
The impala always seem to have family destruction. There's a lot of chasing
calling and tailing.
That can lead to a mass jumping effect.
Impala males spend a lot of time and energy collecting
maintaining group of females. Something's up
he went to his wives. It is a jackal
who is not interested. It is made surprise.
The zebras are xxx.
The impalas are competing and two male giraffes
are making ritual fight probably
to establish dominance.
And then come to xxx,
the impalas efforts paid off, so
the Zebras. Yes,
that back of the zebras crossing quite relaxed alongside the traffic.
But this cyclist is going to have an interesting ride to work
It is a giraffe crossing. One
becomes two becomes
three then four
then five. How do you move
five giraffes? He drops something in the frame.
They are behind you.
They just keep on coming. After all
it is their corridor, There are right a way
in fact should the flower farms fail
because of lack of lake water. This investment in wildlife may prove invaluable
to see what animals so confided so easy
and so close is a privilege, but they can be hazards as we see.
And the baboons simply don't care
Mating in the queue.
The corridor can be shared by people
and wildlife.
Impalas wait patiently for the right time to cross
Historically,
Local canyons have eaten bush because is a natural food
Here both parties seem to have forgotten that the poaching may increase
as bush turns into a business. Giraffe skins
can be used to make buckets and for the tourist souvenir trade.
This is like xxx species but to what extent giraffes can continue to walk
the corridor in safety
remains to be seen. Such
is the people pressure. A solution may
surprisingly lie in the hands of shoppers in supermarkets
thousands of miles away. That's
if they find out what's happening the lake Naivasha
and its water.
For this young giraffe the prickly pear edge
is all too affected.
But mostly
the migration keep streaming through.
The speed bump certainly help.
Numbers of xxx increasing again as the rain
take some pressure off the lamb. The master will always be looking for more
grazing grounds and water supply as a squeeze times on them and their
livestock
to which they are so devoted and on which
this so dependent. There is only so much grass and water to go around
although the giraffe have the advantage, they can feed from ground
to treat old.
It could be that female who lost her care after mother lake
is now back in business.
This may not look too enough to us.
Please just what concern a male giraffe on an important signaling device
with hints of things to come. Perhaps back in Hell's Gate National Park
when she lost her made to some months ago. The only dangerous
animals to her here is man. In the sequence of supply and demand
apparently innocent at this time. Behind the green grass
the greenhouses squeezs impala and giraffe.
Home of the augur buzzard is among the occasions.
This is no abundant wildlife from multiplying warthogs
to millions migration white butterflies house with the rain
depends on the way the whole watershed is managed from the rain falling on the
mount forest but the lake basin
to the flower growers. The flow workers use it
and including increasingly steam power
which is derived from the link water way below ground.
They meet the pylons again,
so do the impalas and zebras. They must read their way between the flower
business
and the power business. Heading for the safety of Hell's Gate
a protected place. What is it?
When the going gets tough the master go grazing
sometimes in national parks.
And the water is a lifeline,
the stretches all the way for an endangered late called Lake xxxx
to the supermarket shopping baskets of Britain and Europe
A cesarean flower farms Waitrose supermarkets
a part of food or water chain
and are being held responsible for the lake. The Waitrose claims it is
a sustainable source. It is not,
but it could be.
Water is the future.
In no way could die lake be considered a
sustainable source,
but it could be. There is a management plan
based on scientific research over 25 years
with a budget to repair the lake and help its people
and its wildlife.
If the water goes so does the flower business.
The jobs,
the tourism and those giraffes amongst
much else.
No water nothing left.
When the volcanic ash cloud from Iceland grounded aircraft,
thousands of flower workers were laid off and the industry was estimated to be
losing
two million dollars a day. A rose only lives for a week
so three million balloons were dumped. That is perhaps
just a warning blip compared with the effect of a dried-out lake.
In April 2010, it was reported that Waitrose supermarket sales rose
26.9 percent to 92.2 million pounds.
Tesco is thriving to. It would surely be good in the competition that's
increasingly
green in tooth and claw for supermarket to be able to say
it's saving the lake.
After all the name is on it.