Towards the elephants closest living
relatives, manatees and dugongs
still spend their lives in the water.
Elephants in Africa
lives south of the Sahara Desert. Some
live in grasslands
called Savannah. Summers here are very
hot,
so these elephants have large
years to found their bodies, and the
wrinkly skin helps too.
After a shower or bath, moisture gets
trapped in all the nooks and crannies
others can,
and helps keep them cool. Other elephants
live in the tropical forests of central
and western Africa.
These elephants have a smaller body and
tasks than the savanna elephants.
The elephant cousins in Asia
are also smaller in size. Their bodies
are suited them moist
Asian rainforest were cooling off is
easier.
His floppy ears aren't nearly as big as
an African elephants,
and his gray skin is less wrinkled.
This
African bull elephant may weigh as much
as eighty people
or six cars. His heart alone
can weigh as much as a young child. He's
also got really big feet,
up to one and a half meters, about five
feet around.
And his brain is larger than all
other land animals.
A bit larger even than ours.
But big is just the beginning
that crock has literally thousands of
muscles,
but there are no bones so it can move in
any direction.
It is so sensitive, it can pick up
a single blade of grass,
and get so strong
it can carry a tree trunk.
They don't actually drink with their
crock to pour water into their mouths.
A big elephant like this one could suck
up about three gallons,
thats 10 leaders at a time.
The truck is really just an extension of
his upper lip and nose,
which has evolved over many thousands of
years. It's the perfect tool
for reaching high or low to eat.
For scratching an itch,
and for clearing a path through the
brush.
Elephants are great communicators. They
talk to each other with the large
repertoire,
growls, grunge, smart, some roars
Allowed trumpeting
gives warning and gathers the herd. Most
telephone communication is so low,
we can't even hear it, but his low
frequency rumbles can be heard by other
elephants
far away.
They may also communicate by sensing
vibrations through the soft skin on the
pads at their feet.
This guy will spend most of the day
eating, putting away nearly 400 pounds,
180 kilos of food each day.
That means elephants pass a lot of
smelly methane gas,
and they produce a huge amount of poop
called dung.
It's not so much to look at, but this
elephant poop is very important.
It is proceeds from the plant some leaves
that the elephant has even.
On a dung beetle rolls around or carries
it below ground.
It helps replant new grasses increased.
In fact some seeds won't even germinate
if they don't pass through the elephants
digestive tract.
In some areas, without elephants
a third of all big tree species would
completely die out.
Elephants contribute to the survival of
plants and other animals in many other
ways.
Her journey through the high grass
provides food for birds by disturbing
small reptiles
amphibians and insects. The depressions
left by her footprints contract rainfall,
giving smaller animals a place to drink.
Elephants are so important to the
biodiversity where they live,
but they are considered as the keystone species.
Like the center stone
or keystone that holds up an arch,
elephants play a critical role in
supporting their ecosystem.
These huge animals were also very
important to people.
In Asia, elephants have had a special
role in society and culture for
thousands of years.
They provide transportation and help
with heavy lifting. Elephants even went
to war.
they were like tax in ancient battles.
There is an elephant guard called
Kenisha
in the Hindu religion. It uses the Lord of
success
The god of education, knowledge, wealth
and wisdom.
Elephants are in fact very intelligent
and self-aware,
right up there with dolphins, heaps and
humans.
They are one of only a few animals
including ourselves,
who can recognize their own reflection
in a mirror.
With many years have memory and
experience,
she knows where to find food and water
during drought.
And other things that are vital to the
well-being of the herd.
Like children,
young elephants are completely dependent
on their family.
Together the herd provides love and
discipline.
They teach the camps how to find food
and water,
even how to behave. That strong bond
starts from the very beginning. A mother
elephant
is pregnant for almost two whole years
before she gives birth.
This baby may look small next to its
mother,
but already it weighs more than 250
pounds,
one hundred ten kilos.
A baby elephant needs to touch or be
touched by its mother
or another close relative every few
seconds for reassurance.