In Europe a years ago, did a top 100 list of
things that people want to do when
before they died in England, and do you know
what was number one?
Swimming with dolphins! Where they have
the opportunity to take photos with our
dolphins,
kisses, handshake, hugs, they get a ride.
from our dolphins. I think it's an
extremely foolish thing to allow people
to do. I don't think it's safe for the
animals, I don't think it's safe for the
people. A lot of people have been injured in
some of the dolphin programs. A lot more
than you think. People really don't
think that visiting area with dolphins
pose any kind of danger because it is
perception is that this is
completely safe environment to which is
probably not.
Dolphins defecate and urinate three
times more, a regular dolphin, three times
more than the average human being every
day.
So this dolphins living its in
its own. People material its own urine
and if you don't do something about that
then with chemicals or with ozone or
some type of a mitigation, then basically
you get a feathered pit.
The water goes bad so they're
constantly adding chemicals to the water,
chlorine, caustic, soda.
All types of algaecides and polymers and
copper sulfate to make it blue,
but they're constantly finding the fact
that these dolphins are crapping and
peeing in the pool and in large
amounts every day. And we know that most
of the fecal material which is actually
microbial biomass germs, which are
dissipating
its water. Education by dolphin there is
about,
I don't know the numbers back, in the
trillions and trillions of bacteria are
released. Self cleaning properties for
natural ecosystems but in the enclosed
facility, which you can do you can just
to poul maybe
chlorine to the water or try to a filterate
that it is efficient or not efficient
against disease-causing bacteria is
clear. If you were there during the days
of the high concentration, you are at
risk of getting dysentery of getting
skin infections that turn
into a flesh-eating bacterial infection.
There's any number of things that you
you're buying when you buy a ticket to
these places to put dolphins and whales
and sea lions on public display. Water
quality can be a issue because what
happens is that the load of the animals
and the technology of changing its like
the ranges can be very extreme, right?
So all is on chlorine, UV. There's all
different parameters,
so some trainers, I've known have
developed like chlorine, rashes.
There is no way to immediately fix some
of these high coliform counts that can
be generated sometimes generated by the
dolphins themselves. Sometimes generated
by the hot water that we you know suffer
through in the summer time when it gets
above 90 degrees down here, there's just
it's a petri dish.
It's not possible to swing without
swallowing.
some water. Some of the bacteria will be
coming really into the gastrointestinal
tract and second treatise. Of course, you
are not protecting your skin as well
right.
This purification system, good question,
is it working in a way that immediately
filter the bacteria?
I don't think so maybe some bacteria
even not trapped by the filters so they
actually circulating in that system and
probably become like endogenous
population of this aquarium, and maybe when
even without modification, may course some
problems for visitors. There are many in this
aquarium, any facilities that
have closed circuits filter system, given
amount of water in the tank is
recirculated through the filters, and
then the filters are back washed and
that lowers the water level and
they add fresh water to it out of this
came back clean water. Just a constant
recycle. The water quality conditions
whether it's a natural Lagoon or an
artificial environment, are replete with
bacterias viruses and infectious
materials, that if an animal is
compromised because of a wound or
compromised because of poor health or
immune deficiency.
You are basically going to end up with
an animal that needs a lot of medical
attention and it can ultimately die just
from the water quality conditions.
Medical reports, new crops reports and
marine mammal inventory reports that you
can find with the National fishery
service that show you that animals have
died from bacterial infections and those
bacterial infections come from the poor
water quality that always exist. What is
actually
we happening in these systems, if there
are so big bacterial loop that may pull
the danger for visitors.
If there are some bacteria which are
coming from humans and can infect the
animals in some studies has been shown
that too.
For example, so call the folk cause
meets the system rays which is
abbreviated MRSA.
It's extremely dangerous because it can
be transferred to my animals, can be
transferred from animals to humans, from
humans to animals and wife sources. Any
infectious diseases that whales and
dolphins in captivity may have, that
could be transferred to a trainer or to
other animals.
The diseases that they get are due to
the stresses. They get pneumonia a lot
from just poor circulation,
poor cardiovascular operations. All of
that just slows down in captivity and so
sometimes they get, you don't just common
everyday diseases that usually they're
immune system is able to defeat, but
because they are under such stresses,
their immune system just can't keep up.
Sometimes with that the stresses
they get ulcers.
They get two infections skin
infections. They get a lot of different
kinds of infections. As I came to work
you know with a common cold and sneezing
and coffin and
next thing I know we've got a dolphin or
two that's doing sneezing and coughing.
Respiratory ailments that they have to
be put on antibiotics that has happened.
Dolphins are highly intelligent and when
they indicated, I think they're
subjected to the higher level of stress
probably than than any other animal.
Because the kind of material to brain
and nervous system the a supposedly is
subjected to the higher level of stress.
As we know that stress affects the
immune system, it suppresses the immune
system, and to the bacterial load also
changes and colleges changes, it's also
not clear.
And so when you are for example swimming
with these animals, you know you'd better
hope they're healthy and that you're
healthy because otherwise it could
problems. And certainly trainers have had
problems, and i believe that a few of the
animals that have died in the past die
because they've been exposed to
something from people. Whether it was a
member of the public or trainer,
more likely a trainer. Because the public
generally speaking doesn't interact
closely enough and often enough and for
a long enough time with the animals to
be a real hazard where a strange course
of their everyday. Diseases the Dolphins
get, we can also get. The diseases that we get
we can transfer the dolphins and vice
versa.
There's any number of combinations that
are possible. Diseases that can jump the
species barrier.
Alright so tuberculosis for example, we
can give tuberculosis to marine mammals,
brucellosis brucellosis is a is a
disease of cattle for example. It can
jump to cetaceans and then it can jump
from stations to humans.
So these are, there are several viruses
and bacteria that can jump from
citations to people and people to
stations. For moving fiction
which probably also can be and in the
various is white,
Bruce for example, a dolphin maybe we can
be also easily infected with this
fungal infections like Candidiasis a
spiritual this type of microbes. Because
i was in the fish house with fish blood
and in and out of salt water with fish
blood and seeing the dolphins.
I got such a bad infection that they
thought that I had leukemia and
ultimately had to have a limp snowed in
my left inguinal lymph node removed as a
result of that.
In my past, not only have I witnessed
some accidents, I've been the victim of
some I've had broken ribs.
I have a finger here that looks very
abnormal because of the infection from a
sea lion.
I've seen people ran and I've seen people
bitten rake marks that just shredded
their forearms.
If there's any number of
situations that don't always happen in
the wild because the animals get a
chance to choose whether they want to
stay or go.
And you won't get hurt if you impose
yourself on these animals. You can
get hurt just like you do enough with a
dog that doesn't want your attention
you're going you're going to get bit.
You do enough to chase or try to go out
and touch a marine mammal who doesn't
want to be touched and they will turn on
you.
Usually the effects of captivity are to
make a whale go quite crazy. With what
happened with Tilikum he has killed
three people and apparently he would
just went crazy from the effects of
being in captivity because they don't do
that in the wild. At different varying
degrees you get some animals have seen
panic attacks in wales and it's just
like watching a panic attack in human.
It's not nice the psychological effects
of living in captivity causes all sorts
of stresses. The stress of of sheer
boredom.
For one thing of having nothing around
that would be like us living in a plain
white room with no windows and no
pictures on the wall and no other
company.
Some animals that develop neurotic
characteristics, they rub themselves, they
bang their heads against the wall,
they choose things. In the effects of the
stress of captivity the stress of the
show schedule, the stress of eating dead
fish.
You know it's it's not it's not the diet
these animals are use to having. As it's
the same thing over and over and over
every day the same blaring music and the
same clapping trainers in the same
routines.
There's any number of experiences that
would certainly qualify as aberrant
behavior, that in my opinion is caused by
the the stress of captivity. But we give
depressants to the to the petting pool
dolphins because that environment of
being stuck with people grabbing at you,
created dolphins that were very
aggressive and returned in the biters,
and those animals were given depressants
on a regular basis to control their
behavior.
Some animals become aggressive
especially the males, because of their
captive situation. A lot of people and
injured in some of the dolphin programs a
lot more than you think.
There's several reasons why often it's
not reported. One is most people who get
attacked by dolphin and a swim with a
dolphin program are made to believe it
was their fault.
And because they are led to believe that
dolphins are somehow magical happy
creatures that would never hurt a fly.
They believe it, they actually feel that
they must have done something wrong to
make that dolphin bite them or make that
dolphin ran them and so they don't
report it because they feel guilty.
So that's one reason why they
don't report it, the other reason is
because the facility itself often
encourages them not to report it, and I
believe in a couple of cases they've
actually bought people off,
not too settled you know gave them some
money so they wouldn't report it. But the
fact is is that people are injured in
some of the dolphin programs a lot more
than you think it's usually mine are not
saying they're like you know mall or
anything but their bruised
their fractured or broken bones,
they're bitten, they have to get stitches
maybe you know five stitches maybe a
hundred stitches.
You know it happens a lot more often
than you think
safety is guaranteed by the hush money
that is given to pay for whatever injury
and
whatever money is made to make sure
those people go out don't go out and
soon if they do sue in many cases, the
it's an out-of-court settlement so
nobody can talk about it. There's a gag
order that's put at the end of any
serious injury.
I do know that when it comes to the the
several people who have been injured at
sea world, they many times have settled
out of court and then given an extensive
amount of money in exchange for not
talking about the details of their
injury and how this happened and
certainly not having any further
conversation about being injured, so
there's all kinds of ways
you can find yourself in a hospital as a
result of buying a ticket to see these
poor animals as slaves.