As the oh sorry for
real coniferous forests commonly known
as a Tigon stretch out to meet the
Pacific Ocean. The brown bear begins to
loses status as the national symbol of
Russia. They are
in the ridges of Secretaria Mountains. The
bear meets his great rival, the amur
tiger, proud, solitary and animatic
predator. The another tiger is one of the
largest of all the tiger sub-species
on earth and the early one will
survive in the snow drifts. Few
other countries in the world can build
such great treasure.
The tiger is one of the nature's
most efficient hunters. In
contrast to lions, wolves and hyenas
will survive by communal hunting. The
tiger hunts alone.
He taxes his kingdom and
live unnecessary. Taking as much as it
needs to survive.
Many after successful hunts,
survivors can relax and enjoy a
box of second of peace and quiet for the next
couple of days.
Mild bow, red deer, seeker row and
other prey give a communal sight of
relief.
not know what those are glad the Lord
know about on social changes i will try
yet the discs about to provide our wiki
a little more diet and water on
television is also working it will
operate thousand yes it has got your
miss yourself here in those awful for
you I wish me . During the nineteen eighties,
the boreal forest bounded in wild boar,
tigers were happy and well-fed.
Tigresses gave birth to many cubs,
assure that their litters
would not face starvation.
This was for the first time in 40 years
of the more tiger conservation efforts
that the tigers population had hit high
with tigers colonising every potential
range, but in 1983 unfortunate struck hit
by candace temple, the wild was doing
there to extinction. Tigers turn to red
and rouldeer as not alternative source of
food. However it never rains but
it pours.Deep snows and the
winters of 1985 through 1987 brought
about a massive loss of angular prey.
With the bo real forest empty, it was
virtually no food for the tiger to find.
During the famine, tigers started to
cramp populated areas
snatching dogs and attaching of livestocks.
In the winter of 1986, tiger
tracks were found at the trolley bus
station in the suburbs of the city of Alabasta
causing great panic among
residents. The Communist Party responded
quickly with a night of civilian
protection, a special brigade was going
to control big predators. Literally
it's stood for war on invasive tigers.
According to official permits, 48
catholic tigers were killed during the
anti-tiger crusade.
At the time, these killings went
unbastion. Tigers that had come
out from the depths of the forest were
perceived as dangerous and receive death
sentences without investigation on trial.
During that time, it’s a burren
boreal forest had not yet been
pillaged by Huracias timpeldealers and
was still reaching Richard Korean pine.
It was here that the most
cautious tigers found their refuge.
Those of them who has learnt
their lesson well. Man is the most mortal
danger and you should keep away from him
ideally beyond the distance of a
rifle shot.
Korean pine forests are the unique ecosystem
in the Taigon. Winter and
Summer, these forests enjoy a special
microclimate with this own oxygen plant rich
and antimicrobial irons and fit inside.
Rich soils and a
great diversity of plants and animals
are to be found here. In a plentiful year,
the pine yields up to half a ton of
cones per hector which proves our
great peace of birds, animals and people
they like.
The nuts present a very tasty and
rich product and it used
to produce oil and milk. They much larger
than Siberian pine seeds and keep their
nutritional value longer. Probably be the
one is electrically area is beautiful it
which the cranials week. After the
collapse of the Soviet Union, coniferous
forests were very often the own
source of income for inhabitants of
remote villagers. People used to value and
protect the green pine. Local theaters
the infamous look of Russian capitalism
don’t. A new breed of people came to
the thai gosh, these were people who
wanted only to father their purses the
green pine capitalists. The looters of
the tigon pursuing short-term interests
abroad chainsaws and went cutting into
the boards. However following a strong
public protest, a ban was imposed on
industrial logging of pine in 1989.
The natural father's the population of
angulus which managed to survive in
conifer the city's forest was quick to
recover. The process which ran parallel
to the recovery of the in-law tiger
which had suffered severe losses in the
war with man.
The start of the nineteen
nineties, so the iron curtain fall.
The borders were open, premorial
became in debt of the
smugglers from nearby China, ready to buy
up the whole of the tigon. Nearly
every hunter went striking rich by
killing a tiger and selling his skin to
Chinese buyers at fabulous prices.
Many were tempted to try their luck and
a new war on Tigers began.
new two is cool talking install million
you're only gonna crash down. Yet
tigers brought fortune to nobody.
Hunters died in the Taiga as well
some of them from the teeth and claws of
tigers they stopped. in the educated
importantly spiritual existence
medically possible
The repercussions of the tiger war could be
felt all over the world. In 1994, the
Worldwide Fund for Nature launched this
operation in the Russian parade with
the project designed to protect them or
tiger.
Upon the initiative, the
number of non-government organisations, a
special inspection team tiger were setup
which can initially endured with a broad
scope of responsibilities. Seven
anti-poaching brigades are established
to protect anglers, the tigers’ prey.
With the support of the WWF the Phoenix
Pond, inspectors managed to confiscate
78 tigers’ heart, over 30,000 poaches
were obtained, 4,000
rifles were confiscated and over
500 lawsuits were filed.
Due to this joint effort, the community
managed to put an end to our treasure’s
bridges of all limits by poachers and
succeeded in stabilizing the tiger
population numbers around 450
individuals.
However the end of the Iron Curtain did
not found to bring evil, it also
triggered rapid development of
international cooperation in the field
of Science.
On the initiative of the Morris
Honaker Institute and the
Pacific Institute of Geography in the
Furies branch of the Russian Academy of
Sciences. The secretary Aldona
Reserve saw a successful launch of the
Russian-American Amur Tiger project
which inaugurated invaluable practices
capturing life Tigers inmobilizer then
the dots and transporting them to
designated places. A new
breed of Russian professionals didn't
take long to emerge
and thanks to an effective mix of
information from radio collars and
traditional tracking methods.
Scientists began to gather a large
amount of new data about tiger ecology.
This then formed the basis
for Russia's national strategy of amur
tiger conservation.
science economics
this wasn't that
While his mother relaxes taking
her nap in the bushes away from the
scorching sun and blood sucking
mosquitoes after an exhausting hunt, a
well-fed offspring goes to play hunt
along the back of the stream. He regards
himself quite grown-up, a big tiger who
can do everything for himself.
However, for the time being, he's so awkward
that not only anguluars but the frogs from
the stream see him and run away in
dismay. This gives him huge
pleasure at this stage of his
development, he sees in himself are
terrible and all inspiring master of his
domain.
Still, some animals do not want to scare,
it seems no need. They are
hunter seems to be spitten by the
proportions of an adult female red
deer. Attempt to frighten a
Himalaya black bear and is in vain as well.
But they will come
a day for the cub will undoubtedly see
him again.
Just then the true monster of
the realm becomes apparent. A
full grown male tiger is on a tour of
inspection around his property.
The tiger cub faces great danger who
knows the big tiger has on
his mind what move his in. He's
not necessarily cub’s father. He might
kill another tiger’s cub quite without
a second thought. In fact among
tigers, even natural fathers do not
despite affection the formulas towards
their offspring and they're not avoid
and weary. The father’s
opposite female tigers are
ready to do anything for their cubs
The cubs sake a mother tiger will challenge
male and considerably larger and
stronger animal but the big
male prefers not to have anything to do
with this protective mother. After
rolling his territory, there are many
other shady Korean pines for him to rest
under. This family is lucky,
their territory lies
inside a nature reserve where
logging is illegal.
However in Russia, protected areas makeup
just twenty percent of the tigers’
habitat, so most other tigers are much
less lucky.
Not every shot a poacher takes turns out
deadly ,wandering the forest so the
Secretaria are a great number of
wounded animals. More or less every other
tiger carries some ability and some sharp
under its skin. This exhausted and
wounded animals unable to catch up a boar or deer
often secret villages and
settlements in such an easy field.
The inspection tiger group set up a
unit called calvic tiger which to deal
with such situations.
However this time in
contrast to the nineteen eighties, the
unit included not only good marksman but
biologists and scientists as well
armed with their own special equipment.
This also a new game so drastic
changes. From now on, every tiger appear in the
village or settlement would be
frightened the way instead of shot, where
appearances reoccurred the invasion
visitor would be captured and examined.
Any tiger who followed and attacked
hunter will be captured at the find. And
ever the tiger should kill and eat
the men, what he was subject to the
ultimate punishment of extermination.
However, things fail to be so simple.
In the remote settlement
of Trinivica, the situation for
capturing tiger who had been killing
dogs seemed ideal. Snow that here was
so deep that the tiger had to plough his
way through depths after his valley.
He could not cover that distances and
had to make use of roads and leave tracks
which get him away without fail. However,
traps failed to catch the tiger and
no tracks were found nearby the roads.
The following morning, news came
from a village 20 kilometers away that
a dog had been attacked that night. New
traps were laid and people started to
search following the roads.
The next morning brought another message
about the morning attack on a dog in a
different place. This pattern repeated
the south of a two torturous weeks.
The corporate work this patch
professionally, never to be seen
more than once in any place. Never
returning to the scene I described,
always staying away from rose.
The solution to this crime spree
when it came was a surprise.
A railway
linking local mining settlement
was being kept clean and maintain in good
condition on the databases by diligent
railway workers. A
perfect route for a tiger who made use
of this functional, practical
infrastructure in Aberham to travel to
unexpected destination as a result
this tiger was never captured.
At another village, Rockavca,
the tiger tried to
attack a car. Fortunate
victim's injuries were not serious
for more than a few scratches.
They stay unsettled 500
meters away from the farm. Apparently,
this convince would be easier to wait for
waste products for slaughter to be
done so he could eat when the coast
was clear.
At first, he was keen for nobody
to detect him and attack him
on the cover of darkness. But
eventually he started to frequent the
place at daylight and displayed no fear of evil.
This type of behavior
posed a serious threat not only
to the livestock but now to people
themselves. On
arriving at the village, the Calvic
tiger team had no difficulty in
determining about the predator was
seriously ill. To shoot the lotter
would have represented no problem.
The tiger was hardly able to drag
his feet along could not run at all and
will switch to something up to just a
few jumps. It was easy to catch up with
him in the open field.
Nevertheless, the team took a courageous
decision to capture the tiger alive.
The object was to give
him a thorough inspection and pronounce
his condition only after a full medical
check-up. A trap was sat at his actual
feeding place.
The following day, the tiger was taken
into custody. He failed to show any
resistance and display a strange
pattern of behavior, different to help
the tigers in a trap.
The specialist immobilised the
tiger and conducted a thorough medical
examination. Quick to establish that
irreversible processes were away with no
chances of improvement, the team decided
to put the tiger down by injection.
This gorgeous male tiger got into the
apoachers now but
he was not lucky enough to escape a sad
fate. He was found not quite a trouble,
but by good people who did not touch him
and reported his discovery.
The convict tiger team managed to combine the
tiger was to the light. question you were
really cliquey but it's a lift sure you
can associate a bit yourself
Tiger was immobilised and delivered to a
special confined unity for treatment.
After here successfully undergone a
series of treatment procedures to help
him recover his health, he was
immobilized again fitted with a radio
collar and deliver the full comfort to
his native hunting grounds.
Ven aquí want to be rebooted but the
lesson of Virginia a tmobile. Nasty start
of the third millenium, so
relations between man and the tiger rise
to a new level.
From then on, the death penalty
for convict tigers without
investigation and trial will be
cancelled.
It takes a tiger over a year to
muster all the intricacies of hunting
alone under the guidance of his or her mother.
At this stage, the target
against the coming of age gains
independence has defined his or her own
hunting ground, his territory. This
is the most difficult task
as the prime hunting grounds are
typically monopolised by adult tigers.
A tigers hunting ground is not just a
section of forest, it is an area where he
must catch and kill no less than 50
bunglers each year. Those that
escaped and remain uneaten should
divide long enough to replenish the prey-stock
and enable the tiger to know
enough shortages.
Tagar is not supermarket, no animal
agrees laterally to prey a tiger
even a skilled adult tiger
concludes many hunts without dinner
though he may be king of the tagar and the
other tiger is no long distance running,
his strengths lies and sprints and rushes.
Tigers fight with each
other for control of the best
territories. Those who failed to fire
the plot of land in the
reserve do their best to settle in
hunting leases where wildlife biologists
have greatly increased angular numbers.
The ambulition of the death
penalty is an historical milestone for tigers.
Yet it pre-supposes the
establishment of special facilities
for probation of these laws ship where
left straight and narrow.
In theory this seems quite
understandable,
however in practice things are far from
idea. All
types of cubs are trying to survive
without the protection of their lost
mothers regular come to villages to
catch stuffs such tigers
first and to a private facility that
tiger special inspection unit. From now
on, the heavy financial burdens of
treatment and feeding are taken on by a
non-government organization. With the
castle powerscorin time, they still
have a long way to go, not to prison
but to another private facility
based in herbarrow’s region at the
cliff rehabilitation center for wild
animals. The tiger cub begins to
shake over the stress of transportation
in a special cell or the done it is only
to leave at night.
Imagine by his reaction
to inanimate objects such as an
automatic video camera, it has
been no performance so far. The tiger
has retained in fear, a sign that he can
safely undergo rehabilitation treatment.
When the small tiger against his
strength, a door is opened to lead
into a spacious confined areas where he
will have to master the basics of
hunting learning to catch real-life food
to eat. His reaction to video cameras
confirms that the sub-adult tiger has
preserved fear of human beings
which possess the main pre-requisite for his
survival in the wild.
But what is to be done next? Will
he be placed in a zoo or
center circus? In 2002, following an
initiative by the Wildlife Conservation
Society. The inspection tiger unit
set out to conduct a bold
experiment. Two young female
tigers who had undergone a complete cycle of
rehabilitation where radio collar down
release back into the wild.
His radio tracking data clearly
indicated that those tigresses had
adopted quite well to the taigon.
Each of them had
learnt to hunt on her own and succeeded
in obtaining enough meat to survive.
Each of them had managed through
the confrontations but their’s. Neither
of them came out to villages and no
attempts were made of catching dogs or goats.
Despite this, the
fate of one of these tigresses is
unknown. The callers suddenly went silent
several months later. The other tigress
managed to establish a hunting ground of
Iran which is solve through not only the
winter but also the following spring and
summer hunting foreground wild boar.
Till now, the fate of the more
tiger has been lying in the hands of the
human citizens of pre-memorial will share
their territory with the tiger.
The new edge has brought new troubles.
Now it is not only
individual tigers, but the whole
tiger population that faces danger.
The tigers living in this in
casting jepardy. The bound commercial
Korean pine logging has been replaced
violately but also often predict so-called
maintenance cuttings.
According to official WWF statistics, the
20 hundreds sole cuttings of up to
half a million cubic meters of Korean
pine each year.
Even this ban has been lifted according
to the new Russian forest code,
now Korean tree forest in time
habited of the subject to merciless
logging.
From the moment the first large appeared
on the banks of the more river know how
the Russian government has declared his or her
her personal commitment to the cause of
tiger presentation. But one Summer,
Vladimir Putin set out on the journey to
the Kronotsky Skin Natural Reserve to put
the high-tech GPS collar on an
immobilised tiger having planted their
case on hair, she subsequently spoke
about his government's responsibility
for the preservation of the title as a
symbol of national heritage.
This case turned a new chapter in the
history of relations between man and
the amur tiger. Today, three tigers
where are their next satellite
analyse to put in helps
the academic research projects in one
reserve will spill over into a
long-term national conservation program
supported by the Russian government.
As the Ausurial coniferous forests commonly
known as they Tigon stretch out to
meet the Pacific Ocean. The brown bear
begins to lose his status as the
national symbol of Russian.
There in the ridges of secret alien mountains,
the bear meets his great rival, the amur
tigon, the proud, solitary and animatic
predator. The amur tiger is one of the
largest of all the tiger sub-species on
earth and the early one which survives
in the deep snowdrifts. Few other countries
in the world can boast such great
treasures.
We were busy with the final credits when
a call for action came in the studio in
the vicinities of the city of Asterisk.
An adult tiger was visiting a hunting
base at night causing the frightened
watchman to call the helpline of the
Department for hunting inspection and a
special inspection tiger unit. By the
time the specialist arrived, the tiger
had been found maniacally prosecuting
slowly looking traffic trying to bite it’s
wheels. The behavior of this
tiger was clearly abnormal. Such an
unusual tiger definitely perth a threat
to the residents of the nearby settlemet
of Alisvaka. As a
result, a decision was taken to
immobilise the beast to examine him
formally. The tiger display the
same pattern of behavior as a tiger who had
died the previous year in the clear
rehabilitation center.
However there is no need for
drawing any preliminary conclusions or making any
other pronouncements on his
health. After the
tongue had been placed in special cage,
biological samples were taken to
determine whether there were any
possible viral infections or other
causes of such abnormalities. The pattern
of behavior of this tiger greatly
resembled one that was observed in the
tiger last year on the flight of a Star
Cabarrus Highway where the tiger cause
jams and posed a hurdle to traffic. He
was captured delivered to the Cliff
Rehabilitation Center and died there despite
efforts by staff. He died of Canna Hestemple.
Incidentally on the same day as the
truck tiger was found, experts from
special inspection tiger team and the
department for hunting inspection
captured another tiger at the other
end of Premoria, a small one. This often
tiger cub made his living at a dumping
ground near the village.