In bustling Surabaya, on the Indonesian island
of Java, this is a hot ticket, particularly
at the weekend. It'll cost you a dollar fifty
to step inside the Surabaya Zoo and join the
crowd. And every week 10,000 people wander
through what was once considered one of the
best zoos in South East Asia.
It's a relatively affordable day out for local
families who appear to enjoy themselves but
seem oblivious to the condition of the residents
and their enclosures.
These days, Surabaya Zoo is more of a house
of horrors than a wildlife wonderland. : "I
think Surabaya Zoo is one of the zoos
that never been approved as a zoo because
the facility and the condition of the animal
is not good at all".
"I reckon right now it should be quarantined.
I think it should be closed. They need to
step in now and they need to quarantine that
place right now. It's a
disease carrying death zoo".
Sri Penta has the unenviable task of trying
to care for the zoo's residents as best she can.
And as this sunny, energetic curator shows
us around, it's clear that the job in front
of her is overwhelming."The animals died suddenly.
The cause varies - the number of animals in
the cage...
too many males within a group... the health
factor... the poor environmental conditions
in the cages... these are probably some of
the factors that caused the death of the animals".
Everywhere you look, there are stark and confronting
examples of animals in squalid, cramped conditions.
Australian camels appear sick and emaciated.
Australian pelicans are crammed in wing to wing.
Some animals appear to be begging to be let
out.
"Well, we're close to the animals on a daily
basis -
and when there are so many deaths within the
last three months, of course, we felt very
disappointed. We feel a sense of loss".
About 50 animals have died
in just three months, including this adult
orang-utan on the day we arrived.
Beyond these walls Indonesia's orang-utans
in Borneo and Sumatra are endangered. This
baby male orang-utan may survive. His parents
rejected him so he's being kept away from
the zoo's other diseased apes. It's extraordinary
that they've escaped human threats in the
wild, but here in a place they should be safe
and healthy, they're anything but.
: "Most of all because of the holding facility
they've got is very poor. The humidity is
very high and they are very dark inside and
it's easily transmit diseases one
to the others and the second thing is, the
exhibit is very old, mostly left over by Dutch
maybe 50 years or 70 years ago".
Tony Sumampau is one of Indonesia's most respected animal experts, and he's particularly concerned
about some vitally important residents - Surabaya
Zoo's Sumatran tigers.: "They have no room
for exercise, for these three tigers in Surabaya Zoo.
They have no sunlight when they are growing,
so until now they don't have any facility
for them to exercise, to climb the tree, to
going up, jump up and jump down and things
like that - that makes their muscle becoming
weaker and weaker every day and the food is
not very good as well".
The appalling condition of the zoo's Sumatran
tiger population is perhaps the most difficult
to comprehend. These magnificent creatures
should be the pride of Indonesia, the dominant
predator among the country's exotic species.
But populations have been devastated by development
and poaching. Here at the zoo though, the
picture is no more positive for this critically
endangered animal. "In regard to diseases
that are inside that zoo,
there's tuberculosis, there's hepatitis...
and the animals are also dying of pneumonia".
There are thought to be only about three to
four hundred Sumatran Tigers left in the wild.
In here, 15 share their cramped quarters with
others like this Bengal Tiger.
Sri Penta has seen the best and worst of this
place in her 20 years here. Now, though, it's
so bad she's risking her job showing us the
conditions the tigers are still kept in.
"Why is it not good for the tigers?""It is
not good because the cage is too small, their
resting pen is too small, and humid, as you
can see the floor can't dry, it's humid
and the sun can't get inside. So health-wise
it's not good, it's not healthy, and in the
future it will have an impact on the health
of the animals".
"They're going to die. I have no doubt that
they'll die.
It is absolutely atrocious what they're doing
in this zoo".
The dire plight of Surabaya's tigers has enraged
animal conservationists around the world.
Australian Sybelle Foxcroft is one who came
to Indonesia to try to help, drawn by one
awful life and death struggle, the case of
tigress Melani. "At Surabaya Zoo she was kept
in what I could equate to a dungeon. They
did that because the public were horrified
but then they didn't
really do anything about her and they left
her there for a very long time. So she didn't
get any sunlight, she didn't get anything".
Melani and three other Sumatran tigers were
malnourished and kept in cramped conditions.
Then in 2008 they were fed meat contaminated
with the preservative formaldehyde.
Three tigers died. Incredibly Melani lived...
but only just. And she'd endure five years
of suffering before a public clamour finally
brought government intervention, her evacuation
from the zoo and proper treatment.
Sybelle Foxcroft was instrumental in getting
Melani out of Surabaya. "She's a creature
that has been neglected and abused inside
a zoo that is deemed to care for her.
She's just woken up this morning and she's
not wanting to eat freely like she normally
does, but she's probably looking at everybody
also, being distracted, but her feeding can
take up to about two hours and this is kind
of normal also, but at the moment she just
doesn't seem that hungry".
Melani is recovering at a place called Taman
Safari Park outside Bogor, about a two hour
drive south of Indonesia's capital, Jakarta.
"Well she's
so very frail from her ordeal with this poison
and then starvation. The starvation caused
her body to start
consuming her own organs so right now she's
struggling to live".
Taman Safari is owned and run by
Tony Sumampau and it's dramatically different
to Melani's old home in Surabaya.
It spans 150 hectares and looks less like
a zoo and more like a faithful recreation
of a wild animal's natural setting.
Resident tigers can stretch their legs in relatively
wide open spaces and when they need attention
or when wild tigers are brought here injured
after a run in with a poacher, there are sophisticated
facilities at an on site animal hospital.
"Genetically they are very nice. They are
a wild tiger in fact
so it's good to keep their young to release
them in the wild which is very important".The
Safari Park is looking after 28 Sumatran tigers
who are
under threat."Well someone poisoned him when
he was quite young, less than two years old
I think"."So he's angry with humans since
that I suppose".: "Yeah, but I thought he
was going to die at that time, but hopefully
he's recovered from the poisons and become
a real tiger now"."A real man"."A real man".
The success of Taman Safari leaves Surabaya
in the shade with 1.8 million visitors a year,
it pulls in tens of millions of dollars on
ticket sales alone.
There's restaurants and rides, as well as
merchandise and a kind of side show alley
area that's clearly a profit machine. With
that, the park employs 750 staff and provides
well for its animals. So around about now
you might be wondering why Tony Sumampau hasn't
been called in to sort out the mess
at Surabaya. The short answer is he has, or
or rather had, and the experience goes some way to explaining the intractable problems gripping the zoo in Java and imperilling its Sumatran tigers.
It's a rat's nest of vested interests, power struggles, nepotism, ineptitude and disinterest.
"I think the Surabaya Zoo is
more likely a management conflict between
one management
team and the other team"."But why are the
animals in such poor condition?": "Well, because
they don't understand about the animal welfare
issue".
Tony Sumampau was enlisted to fix Surabaya
Zoo back in 2010. He says he tried to establish
programs to better train zoo keepers to care
for animals and tried to rebuild or renew
animal enclosures, but money was scant and
so was goodwill. The zoo is staffed by people
with family connections and he says the animals'
interests just don't rank as a priority.
"They don't really know how to manage the
zoo but they're just thinking of gaining some
money from the visitor for the purpose of
their own welfare, not the animal welfare.
The things that make the Surabaya Zoo is getting worse and worse".
"It was founded and built using public money
from an idea by journalists at the time. And
it grew to become one of the biggest zoos
in South East Asia".
Earlier this year Tony Sumampau was kicked
out by this woman - the formidable but very
popular Mayor of Surabaya - Tri Rismaharani.
The Surabaya Municipal Council is responsible
for running the zoo and owns the land it occupies.
The Mayor claims a lifelong interest in the
place.
"When I was little, my grandpa always me to
come along to the zoo, and that's why during
junior high school I joined the Surabaya Zoo
Lovers Club.
When I came to the zoo, the condition was
worse than it was when I was little".
Mayor Rismaharani hurled a barrage of accusations
at Tony Sumampau, claiming he was secretly
planning to develop the zoo into a luxury
holiday resort and that he was trafficking animals.
"One year ago the team came to me, and said
there were not enough funds for the maintenance
of the zoo. They wanted to build a hotel...
a restaurant. That's when I got upset - why
did I get upset? Because the zoo is the pride
of the Surabaya people".
"This is just silly you know? I'm helping
for free not for the... for stealing animals
inside the zoo. If I wanted to get the animal
I can ask the Minister - I like this animal
- then I can get it just for free, but I've
never done that, you know. But they keep accusing
me like that. I don't know why"."So you never
took a proposal to them about a hotel?""No,
never. Never. I've never seen one too".
Critics of the mayor in turn claim she has
her own development plans for the central
city site. They accuse her of interfering
for years in its affairs before taking personal
control of the zoo, even though she has no
expertise in the field.
"I think time will tell if what we do is right
or wrong. Conditions were bad back then.
I had to deploy 5000 municipal employees...
to clean the cages... to scrub the cages...
to mend the broken cages... to clean up the
water tanks. There were five thousand people".
It's difficult to reconcile the Mayor's catalogue
of activity with what we saw at the zoo. In
the sweltering Indonesian heat, animals still
swam in and drank from heavily polluted water.
The mayor has declined offers of assistance
and expert advice from animal welfare groups.
"About.. over a year ago I wrote to the Mayor
and basically asked her to please, you know,
implement some humane care in Surabaya Zoo
and... you know along those lines, just trying
to be supportive as well and offering aid....
and I didn't get a response from her".
"Why do you think the Mayor has refused help?"
"I have no idea. I do not know why she's refusing
help. She has been offered help from a lot
of organisations around the world and my impression
that I'm getting is that she's done some very
good work around but she is not.... she's
got engineering degrees and city planning
degrees. She is not an animal skilled person.
She is not a zoologist or a wildlife-ologist
or any animal ethics qualifications at all.
She's got to leave this one alone and allow
the professionals to get in there and fix
these animals or else they are going to continue
to die".
And as claim and counter claim volley from
one side of Indonesia to the other, the animals
continue to suffer and die.
In some ways the strife at Surabaya Zoo is
emblematic of the nation's
vexed and sometimes hostile relationship with
its wildlife, where humans and development prevail and animals lose.
Out here in the wilds of Sumatra the tiger
has roamed for thousands of years but vast
swathes of its jungle territory are being
turned into farming land. Indonesia's burgeoning
population has pushed ever deeper into the
tiger's natural domain."Even in the wild,
when we're helping
the tiger conflict, villagers are complaining
'Why do you only think about the wildlife
that are taking our livestock? Why not you
think about our life?', you know."
We're on our way to Sesiro in north western
Sumatra. Like many villages it's carved out
of the jungle wilderness, and like some, it's
got its own tiger tale to tell.
Sesiro's home to about 600 people. It's not
the poorest of places in Sumatra - the local
rubber industry offers plenty of work. Villagers
who run small subsistence farms here worry
about losing stock to wild animals. Recently,
though, a tiger claimed a human life.
Adi and his friends work the local rubber
plantations, but illegally harvesting sandalwood
from deep in the national park is a tempting
sideline that can earn a year's salary in
quick time. On a trip into the jungle hoping
to strike it lucky, they came under attack
from a group of Sumatran tigers.
"One of our friends got separated from us
and we saw the tiger get hold of him. We saw
that tiger. And we looked to the other side.
There was another tiger coming at us, so we
hurriedly climbed up the trees".
From that vantage point they saw their friend
mauled to death.
"I've been working a long time in the jungle
and this was the first time I saw that".
The fatal attack horrified the men and traumatised
the village, but the experience made them
respect the tiger and its territory in a way
they'd never thought of before.
They're not the only ones thinking about the
tiger. Slowly the country's tigers are getting attention.
"In the past, for decades, in Indonesian
culture,
people used to feel so proud having tiger's
skin in their house. They were proud owning
elephant tusk. People were also proud to be
able to hunt tigers. And those habits aren't
easy to let go".
Indonesia's Forestry Minister, Zulkifli Hasan,
has come to check the conservation efforts
at Taman Safari Park. His ministry makes the
rules and regulations for zoos but even a
powerful national politician has found it
difficult to solve the Surabaya mess.
"To revitalise it, to improve the way to manage
the zoo, renovating the cages would take an
immense amount of funds. And the entrance
tickets alone won't cover it. The local government's
allocated budget of four billion rupees isn't
enough either. So we need time".
And as if financial and management problems
weren't enough, now nature is throwing in
more problems - evidence is emerging of a
disease developing in already scant wild tiger
populations that attacks the nervous system
and eventually kills the animal.
It's just one reason why so much is depending
on the success of a special breeding program
at Taman Safari Park. When Foreign Correspondent
was visiting the park, vets performed the
first artificial insemination of a Sumatran
tiger in Indonesia.
Semen from a sedated wild male has been injected
into a wild female. If the operation is a
success, the program could help keep the wild
Sumatran tiger population alive.
"I would think now the tiger's number is really at around 300...
350, nothing more than that.
If we can't save the habitat of the tigers
we might lose the tiger in another 30-40 years.
They will disappear in the wild, except in
the zoo".
A great deal rests on the survival of Melani,
the tigress as well. If she can survive the
ordeal she suffered at Surabaya Zoo it will
inspire and encourage all those who've worked
so hard to save her.
"She's a critically endangered Sumatran Tiger.
She has the ability to show affection to the
very species that hurt her so - and to see
an animal struggle
through this sort of thing, you know she wants
to live. It's her will
that's keeping her alive. She's a survivor
and her nature is so very gentle and beautiful". Subtitles End: mo.dbxdb.com