The polar bear, Nanook,
Ursus maritimu, by any name in this beautiful floor
of the Arctic.
Though the polar bear's superiority is not question,
there is an ancient conflict between people and one of nature's most cunning
predators. In the Ottoman, every year conflict erupted to confrontation in a
little town in Canada's Manitoba province.
Hungry polar bears threaten the town and forceful measures are taken to keep
people safe.
The bears are mixed blessing. On the one hand, they are terrifying pests on the
other, they are source of revenue of the Churchill's growing tourist trade.
Fierce! Fascinating!
Polar bear is the top carnivore at the top of the world.
All other animals here are prey. it's nothing personal. It's just life in the
food chain.
The Arctic wilderness are forbidding realm of snow and ice
for more than a hundred thousand years. The polar bear has reigned supreme as
the Lord of this Arctic land.
Humans have tried to conquer this daunting environment. We've made our mark
but can truly call the land our own. The bear alone is securing in sovereignty
of this harsh frosty world.
Exquisitely suited to life in this climate, the polar bear is confident in
its supremacy.
while humans rely on inventiveness for survival under extreme conditions. The
bear has evolved its own xxx rules.
for their existence.
The affairs of mankind about a source of curiosity indication annoys.
The bear is a serious threat.
People aren't the Kings here where the intruders.
Every year, a singular combination of geography and climate brings Churchill's
1,100 people face to face with polar bears. In winter the bears hunt seals on
the bay ice. In summer the ice melts and the bears must come ashore where there
is no food.
The chill winds of autumn draw the hungry bears northward toward the
approaching ice. Churchill's people like directly in their path
As marine mammal, the polar bear is a marvel of adaptation to a world ice and
frigid water. Bears have been observed to swim as far as 200 miles in the open
ocean. Seals are the principal pray but these voracious meat eater seasonally graze
on seaweed.
Arctic foxes are a source of aggravation and amusement.
This is the world's largest land carnivore.
an adult male can weigh up to 1,500 pounds. On the xxx legs,
it may stand more than 10 feet tall.
The source of myth and legend, the bear is considered by traditional people to
be both worthy adversary and close relative.
One story describes the bears as a race of humans who became bears by dressing
themselves and fur.
When an Inuit woman discovered their secret, they became furious and set out
to kill her and every Inuit sense.
The bear's legendary strength is not just stuff of myth. An adult can easily access
seven hundred pounds seal out of its breathing hole and kill it instantly
with one crushing bite from powerful drags.
Females usually give birth to two cubs. In mid-march they emerge from their dens
and had for the day ice. In their first year, 6 out of 10 cubs will die from
starvation accidents or predation.
In the spring mothers, with young cubs can easily be tracked on the open tundra.
Dr. Ian Sterling is a senior research scientist with the Canadian wildlife
service.
Well, this animal here we can see from the air. She's got to come. She's out
of the den .She is fairly lean, so we estimate our way that maybe 350 or 400
pounds and make up a dart for her so that she shall have the right amount of drug.
Research scientists have learned that the safest way to handle large dangerous
predators is to mobilize them of the tranquilizer dart.
The drug wears off in about three hours and the animal unharmed can continue
about its business.
Polar bears are unique to the Arctic, north polar region of the planet. Their
ancient ancestors are the brown or grizzly bears.
Remarkably, the polar bear skin is black.
Hollow white hair follicles like optical fibers conduct warmth down to the skin.
We have the tagged about eighty percent of the adult bears males and
females in this population so this one here
she was caught 13 years ago when she was just like these cubs that she's got
whether. She had her first cub is pretty pretty young. For now thirteen years
later.
In fact almost to the day we've got her with her third letter of of cubs so we
know a lot about to some of these individual bears.
She'll be okay to work with in just a minute.
Cubs are born in midwinter, nursed on their mothers rich milk.
They grow rapidly okay. This is gonna to be the wait for cup one. 25 and a half pounds.
Good big family.
OK, come, come to, 24 pounds.
Over all around the world polar bears are doing just fine.
Population here and Hudson bay is right on the southern limit of where polar
bears can live so if we're going to be looking at things like the possibility
of climate change or other long-term effects were most likely to see them
first in a population that's our living at the limit of its range to start with
The bears in Hudson bay. They are a little bit different from the bears in most
other areas in that they live out on the on the ice and the bay during the winter
but it's all annual ice which means that it melts every summer.
So there's a period of four four and a half months every summer that every
bear in Hudson Bay has to come ashore and fast on the fact that it's got
stored on his body and I think one of the consequences if we get climate
warming in this area. It is that a breakup will occur earlier. Freeze up will occur
progressively later and we'll get more and more bear problems. When problems
between polar bears and people do occur,
it is usually in the autumn. Hungry bears going to town looking for food when
confronted by a human. Most bears would rather go the other way but driven by
hunger they become bold. If they decide to attack and eat a person
they will. Encounter between a human and a bear is very likely to end with one or
the other debt.
Derek Nicrank had a close call right at his front door.
I just letting my dog like this when I was going to work one day and he usually
runs off and down around the corner. And just when I was stepping down she came
running back this way and I guess what happened. It is a bear had grabbed a bag of
garbage and was eating it around the corner.
Then he came charging up this way I turned around when I seen a bear and run
up the stairs and you jumped from the ground right up here.
My dog ran into the corner over there and I turned and ran into here like this.
The bear was right here. He got his paws and through the door and I kicked the
door closed and that pinched his head between the door jam in the door. And he
just sort of backed out to guess it's under and then I got my shotgun and the
bear was right there. And I shout him the first time from here.
He stood back up on his legs and I thought he was going to come back up and
I shot in place more in the driveway. And then, he is around just a little ways over here
and lay down and died.
Lorraine and Danni Allen's scary bear adventure was recorded on videotape by
their nephew, Wayne.
I thought the dog was outside and I went to check the door and there was no dog
there. It was the bear. Ben and I guess. And then I went to check the window
and the
bear was banging on the window so I put my hand on the radio on form we need
to tell damage to come home. Because there's a bear contacting our house we
we got a call over the radio distress call a very high sterically high-pitched
voice stating that a bear was breaking in.
So I got a chair and start banging the chair again the floor and screaming at
him to stop him from coming in the house and he wouldn't listen.
The bear was peeling back the window and next thing that the bear was in the
window and then the bear was in the house and that was it.
The radio went silent.
I rushed back and fun rain-out side in her bare feet.
I grabbed my rifle out of the truck and went to the door walked in.
Bears have his head on the table eating muffins.
It's bacon cupcakes and he smelt the cupcakes and he eat
all of the cupcakes. Well, went to my mind I just had to get him out of the house
before I smash the house all of and yeah I couldn't drive mode. You know you just
can't scare my way once they're inside,
so nothing else I could do but you do it.
You got here now.There's only one shell in that gun and but luckily or whatever
it is
he died with the first shot.
And I don't think anyone here really likes to have to destroy a such a
beautiful animal but in this case here I do believe it warranted it.
There was a human life in danger. In an effort to eliminate fatal encounters
between man and bear, the province of Manitoba, Department of Natural Resources
has established the polar bear alert. Each fall when the Bears start moving
towards town,
a control zone is established. Bear's found within the zone are captured and
placed in a holding facility, popularly known as the polar bear jail. For the
moment this young bear poses no threat,
however his irrepressible curiosity could get him in deep trouble.
The polar bear is a constant presence in Churchill.
In the flesh or in its likeness, it permeates the awareness of the people.
Bear is also a source of civic pride,
but it also looms as a threat to lives.
Their size and outdoor activities make children the most vulnerable to
marauding bears.
Bears are an enduring inspiration and reservoir of income for the native
artists of Churchill.
Myrtle the Mules sculpts more than 250 different designs from pieces of caribou
head.
It's an art form that's original to her. A talent that was mystically given. it's
a gift.
There's no other way I can describe it. I've tried to find a different word for
it but it is a gift. So I do all kinds of bears. I do cute bears mad bears bad
bears even ground for bears.
When my kids were little, I was very paranoid about bears and during
polar bear season I had them the same recurring nightmares about trying to
find places to hide my kids. And the nightmare was that I would be going
through all this
this pressure and fear as I'm trying to hide them all. And just when the bear is.
breaking through the house or through a window,
that's when I wake up.
The safety of the children is on everyone's mind. My name is Lori Ruth. I'm
the natural resource officer here in Churchill and I'm in charge of the polar
bear program.
I'm the guy who catches the polar bears in the fall.
OK and I keep the bears out of town so it's safe for you guys to play. So I have
some of these the polar bear where booklets with me. But I'll do is I'll
just run through with you again.
OK and what to do and what not to do when you meet up with a polar bear.
OK so the first thing I never explore bad smelly areas.
Polar bears really like garbage so if you smell some garbage etc. The bear will
also smell it and that's where he'll head for. Report all bears.
If you do see a polar bear, call our bear line.
675 bear B E A R and that resource officer will answer the phone and we'll
go in and chase the bear away.
From the first chill winds of September through the November freeze up.
Bears are on the move and the Department of Natural Resources is on alert.
Culvert traps are placed in areas that bears have been known too frequent.
The town's perimeter is regularly patrolled. Fatalities occur when unwary
people stumble across bears sleeping in the brush.
Snare traps
are placed along known bear migration routes and checked regularly. When a bear
is trapped,
it is immobilized with a tranquilizer dart and taken into custody.
This bear was caught on the outer perimeter of our our controls on,
so we removed him from the controls on before he entered into town. If you
wouldn't call them was pretty good chance you would have made it into town
and we've got himself of all kinds of trouble and probably would end up being
shot.
The most of the bears that get into trouble in Churchill are some adults who
have not yet become skillful hunters. A starving bear has nothing to lose and
we'll risk anything to feed itself.
This particular bears, a two-year-old which makes up the majority of our
problem bears what it is itself.
These cobs are basically like your teenagers they're cut loose and they
don't know exactly what you're doing and so there they wander around aimlessly
and and get into all kinds of trouble. So they're our biggest problem bears as far
as people bear problems. Before the polar bear alert program was begun in 1985
Ten or twelve bears were destroyed every year in defense of human
life or property. Since then, that number has dropped dramatically.
Now the bear body count ranges from 0 to only one or two killed.
Building d20 is the polar bear holding facility. Mothers with cubs are held here
for a day or two. Healthy young adults are kept for no longer than a month.
The accommodations of Spartan but human, the animals are given water but no food.
Feeding them would hinder that chance for survival in the wild.
Bears will always be bears. Simple as that.
We have to protect the people from bears but we also have to protect the bears
from people.
For those who want to go to Georgia to see polar bears, there are only two ways
to get there.
No roads like the town with the outside world.
The lure of the first hand look at the great white bear draws people from all
over the world to this little outpost on the tundra. Churchill is a
two-and-a-half-hour plane flight from the provincial capital of Winnipeg.
The train trip is a grueling two-day journey.
Interest in polar bears and in polar bear souvenirs approaches of mania
during the October November peak bear season. Though the bears can be
frightening. The visitors, their tracks are seen as mostly good for the town.
To us
the locals we've not only learn to co-exist to the bear.
Now it's bringing so many people.
It's attracted so many people from all over the world who are kind of like
we're really proud to be able to see well we are the polar bear capital of
the world.
We're not about to tell you don't come here it's dangerous. You know if you take
this that the necessary precautions and you listen to your tour guides.
There's no reason why you can't have an a nice safe trip and see the most beautiful
bear world. The best and safest way to see a polar bear close is from a
Tundra Buggy.
These monster machines take visitors out on to keep Churchill in the heart of
polar bear country.
The bears are as curious about the tourists as the tourists are about the
bears. Face-to-face encounters between bear and human are not uncommon.
Polar bears don't seem aggressive or dangerous.
They don't stakeout or defend the territory.
They are absolutely secure in their role as Lords of their domain.
For most of their lives, polar bears are solitary hunters. Ferocious denizens of
the icebound sees fearsome stalkers of the Arctic winter night.
Surprisingly when not competing for food or mates,
polar bears are quite social and engage in complex interactions that positively
delightful visitors to polar bear country.
Polar bears are long lift, very intelligent and learned from experience.
It is likely that they recognize each other and play with the same friends
season after season.
When you're looking at an animal that size it's quite a rush I mean but close
for the first person ever seen.
We're going to definitely has some uncomfortable feeling about it.
Here is a big bear. Reached over there right over the top of the glass.
That's not so bad but when they back up and start to get on the glass you gotta
gotta move along so just let them do their own thing. Obviously we're not here
to see them
that they're not out here to see us.
The first Tundra Buggy was built in 1980 by master mechanic and
back of nowhere engineer Lens Smith. Len cobble together a hand-built cabin to
four-wheel drive truck chassis to make a vehicle that could take a couple of
dozen people out onto the tundra.
Importantly,
to bring them back.
First began to build held 26 people
and now my largest one holds 50.
So it's double in size,
not an engineer so I did made everything about 10 times stronger than it should
be.
But a lot of stuff that came from the factory wasn't strong enough side design
lot of stuff that steering cylinders hoses for protection from one's rights
and that tires breaking beads. I had a designer that wouldn't break the
beads.
It took quite a few years before I got morning's all the little things that
went wrong
down to where I don't have much problems now. Len's goal is for his guests to enjoy
a safe
polar bear adventure.
The ultimate experience is the Tundra Buggy camp that he sets up a cape
xxx. xxx a fortune of polar fan can spend a week or two living amid
and learning about the fabled king of the ice.
The open tundra is a hostile environment.
Temperatures fall well below zero degrees exposed human skin can freeze
within minutes but to a polar bear
this is a comfortable home.
Once Smith works tirelessly to keep his guests warm and well feel
in the two weeks spent at the Cape Churchill camp he will burn around 2,000
gallons of propane.
A week or two in close quarters,
group of strangers
in the middle of a vast ice field and surrounded by marauding carnivores is
not everyone's idea of a fun vacation.
But the adventurous travelers of the Buggy camp love the experience and many
are repeat customers.
The bears are nearing the end of their annual for month fast even dishwater has
some attraction to a hungry bear.
I've never got tired of watching bears, says it's always something new every
year. They they act different they do something different
It's never boring watching polar bears. I can't imagine season going by without my
coming to see the cave Churchill of polar bears. award-winning photographer and
author Dr. Dan Garbage created the Tundra Buggy tour. If one can say you
love an animal without being accused of being an to the anti-morphic. I would say that
I have that kind of relationship with these these magnificent creatures.
They're beautiful and intelligent and if you stay around a place where there's
polar bears for very long,
you'll begin to appreciate them just how intelligent they are.
The adults don't need protein because they finished lowing.
I don't know whether it's more exciting to see the polar bears are more exciting
to see the people. They get so wrapped up in what they see that it's just so very
very exciting.
1976, I met two remarkable animals.
One was the polar bear and the other was here looking at. Through the
endless Arctic night,
ancient people would huddle around the flickering oil-lamp and tell tales of
bear, a creature of mythic strength and epic proportions.
the old man, ancestor, teacher, the burner of winter.
Kubiak,
the ten-legged bear beast. They already have either warm not cold
these and day. Our fascination with bears lies deep within our human experience of
all the ancient animal Gods. Only bear was unlimited and its powers.
In bears we may instantly recognized kinship a fellow being over his
obligations communication.
Familiar mannerisms and need to dominate his living space.
Polar bears have a complex social structure. Females will aggressively
defend their cubs against any intruders.
There are especially ways of large males who are known to kill and eat cubs.
This adult male weighs over 1,000 pounds
but is being persistent, we pursued by a female about one-third his size.
It would see that the male could easily overpower and kill the spirit of female
but instead  he won't.
What's settled their etiquette is in play here. It is a fight with a combative
female too risky to the male's own survival.
We can only speculate and watch as their showdown is transformed into an elegant
and powerful model.
Finally, in a gesture of submission he surrenders, to heard offensive onslaught.
The polar bear alert is a waiting game.
Hold on tomorrow mark winds from the Northwest 60 kilometers an hour actually
get them very xxxx.
For the natural resource officers, it's not a question of if but there will come
to town but when.
Hello, bear alert.
I get your name please.
Very good thank you, bye.
We got a bear between terrible hall in the Complicate.
Drawn by the irresistible smells and sounds of the town,
a hungry and fearless young bear has come ashore near the school and
community center. A potentially dangerous situation for the many people who
frequent the area.
Natural resource officers try to scare the bear away with flash crackers fired
from a shotgun but it is not easily frightened.
The intruder is observed for a short time
and a decision is made to dart and place the bear in protective custody until the
bay freezes.
For the local people it's not a pleasant thing to have to worry all fall about
your kids, especially Halloween. Halloween is the most dangerous time of the year
and there's always a lot of apprehension about that the bears which are always
just skirting your skirts of tone.
So what should you do if you see a polar bear? Walk backwards and no stop.
Right, keep your eye on them, you turn around and run
What's about your bag of candy?
Look like you able to do with that. Don't drop it, just dump it all.
You throw candy away from a bear and then you eat one that he goes after
another one will have a problem back here and then you just run.
Why don't run back at school I guess. So you're going to throw your candies to
xxx the bear.
Yeah thrown them behind.
Well I think if it's a choice between your candy styling and your life.
Don't double.
I pick my candy. And I don't think so
Here's a question for you should you going on Halloween dressed like a
polar bear.
Halloween is celebrated in the midst of bear season and darkness comes early to
the far north.
Wary Boon e has a brief window of time to make a final check for bears in town
before eagle trick or threatens flood the streets and alleyways. Like kids all over
North America, Churchill's usually love the annual ritual of costumes and
house-to-house begging for treats.
No bear is going to spoil their fun.
The town's adults are there to ensure it.
Lots of kids and moving around moving around on the streets and there's a
large number of bears massing right now and keep Churchill
so definitely if polar bear would come to town, it could be a dangerous situation.
Be careful work for the day.
You're gonna freeze out here yes you are coming winter time.
Don't go anywhere.
All quiet in the local cemetery.
All quiet. As long as you don't get bigger then the fox, no problem. Without
warning,
something moving, your pulse quickest.
Your brains works wrong. Fear grips your guy.
Just another kid in a costume, a prankster who didn't get the message
a foolish trick in a town that is on high alert.
White shapes walking in the shadows.
You are not supposed to be running around like this
when your butt shot. That's your brain matter where it's something like that in
it.
Brian Lagoon raises and breathe we're Canadian sled dogs at an isolated spot
on the shore of Hudson Bay. Surprisingly he's not worried that his dogs are
living in the heart of polar bear country.
These dogs are Canadian Eskimo Dogs there
One of candidates for his grades and we keep the most here,
spring summer and fall and the natural environment.
This is very good for them that's the best way to keep them. Any other way
they don't feel safe and secure. Brian's dogs are pack animals they prefer living
close together and rely on one another to sound a warning when danger
approaches.
I don't necessarily keep the dogs in the bears away from each other what I do is
I set a standard that when I'm on the premises
the bears know that they move away from me and keep at a distance so I can come
out into my work and my feeding and my chores and stuff like that. So I mean I'm
careful with the bears but I'm tough with them. They know that I'm at the
greater danger to them than the dogs. I make it that way that I am the greater
danger.
And so they see me and they put head get over their shoulder and they're
looking for that guy again me. Okay.
These dogs are OK well he's crazy. To a half-ton meat eater but hasn't had a
meal for months.
The dogs must look like a smorgasbord. I know that bears are they're carnivores
and all the other stuff too close with him but they still have personality so
you can judge characters of bears in all the body language and so forth and I've
learned to be cautious. Has one thing around them
you can't let your guard down with them, there's still a dangerous kind of work.
You know they have their brutal moments. Once walked from powerful Paul could
instantly kill the aggressive dogs.
The first 10 years I thought the dogs heavy aggression against the bears and
it was much more brutal and savage. Now it's a very more mellow coexistence
because the dogs don't look at the bears as such great enemies.
In the far north bears and dogs have a magical connection.
In one native legend an angry bear is surrounded by snarling dogs,
as he strikes out of them. Bears and dogs begin to glow brightly and wise up into
the sky to become the stars of the Great Bear constellation.
Why this hungry bear doesn't devour the dog is anybody's guess
whatever the reason they seem to have achieved a working peace agreement.
In the company of bears there stands a magic clock,
it doesn't talk her tick and it doesn't take her talk, but it shows you you have
all the time you need
with just what time you've got. So with bears you can be almost anything
Colorado artist Barbara Stone has immersed herself in the life floor of
polar bears .For they only see you for who you are
Whether she renders them realistically or places them in the whimsical settings
for which she is famous.
The bears are her artistic inspiration.
She sees them as a metaphor for experiences in everyday life.
What impresses me about seen more polar bears, a new polar bear in the landscape
is how different their personalities are. Because you see aggressive bears and
swells very timid bears. And I think the important thing about sketching on the
landscape is seeing the bear as a part of the landscape rather than may be working
from photographs at home little bear is just isolated by being in the
environment.
I think I get more of a sense of how their fits into the landscape.
I've been painting polar bears for four years before actually saw one in the
wild and I was curious and the people that were aware of my work wondered how
my work might change when I actually saw bear in the wild but I found that when
I saw and it was actually more amazing and magical that I had even imagined
them in my work.
It is the magic of bears in relation to human life that intrigues Barbara
by placing bear isn't typically human situations.
Barbara offers a different perspective from which to gain insight into our own
lives. On the simpler level,
many people just find her work incredibly charming.
The first time I saw polar bear was in a the vehicle and there were five people
in the vehicle, my daughter was one of them and I was next to the window so I
was able to find myself. I do I with this bear with his nose right against the
window right it might shoulder and it was just thrilling to to be that close
to bear space that actually make eye contact with it. Then
my daughter was sitting next to me lean forward in the bear notice term made eye
contact with her. She's right here it's kind of pounding a little bit.
It finally turned his head as far as it could make eye contact with each person
in the vehicle
what really impressed me about that is I realize that I had made eye contact with
all the people in the vehicle. But it know that we were all separate beings
and it wanted to identify as each. So I was quite impressed by that
You're not really supposed to do that.
Does anybody have any stories about bears and once that you've seen?
I was at my cabin and we hear this
like it was a bear and then I don't know stranding the cap and then my mom is
just a dog growing up. We always used to go to the jump in my we on my mom had a
truck and and then there was a bear climbing up with garbage in his mouth
and he was running after the truck.
This mother and her cubs have not had a successful hunt.
The bay ice is still thin constantly moving. The female leads her young ashore
to drop into the dump for between seal snack.
On a routine patrol the area near the dump,
officers discovered the mother and cubs.
The bears are darted and taken to the holding facility to be measured and
tagged.
Since the jail is nearly full
they'll only be held overnight.
A polar bear airlift is a big attraction for locals and tourists alike.
People can't resist getting a first-hand look at bears unconscious ones.
This hungry trio will be released to the wild far from the town and its
temptations.
Except for being absolutely filthy from their dump adventure
these cubs are in very good condition. Their mother has cared for them well,
They're going to take some bears.
The very compound here and they're going to use the helicopter to transport them
away from the town site. How far to take away? Probably take about 20 25 miles up
the coast north. In about two hours these cubs and their mothers will be awake and
headed for the bat ice. The cubs will spend the winter honing their hunting
skills and learning the ways of polar bears.
Now these is a very our problem in the community before enter. They worry
appetites.
They were got some are close to the community tranquilize that and put in
jail, bad bears. The nobleman or doesn't look so ladylike wrapped in a cargo net
drug to a stupor the helpless victim of human progress.
What will happen to her kind as humans penetrate ever more deeply her frosty
kingdom. Once pure season our toxic soup filled with an alphabet of chemicals
the Inuit natives of this region are believed to be the most highly
contaminated humans on earth. Mother's milk is poisoning babies.
Polar bears have seven times or more of the same toxins in their bodies.
In late November falling temperatures and a frigid northeast wind finally
bring the pack eyes to the western shore of Hudson Bay.
As suddenly as they appeared, the bears will soon disappear into the crack bay
ice.
Free of time for the jail bears
Calven traps are used to transport them to the bay shore where they'll be
released.
A few weeks in jail have not dulled this bears curiosity or perhaps his taste for
humans.
Every effort is taken to make the bears encounter with people as unpleasant as
possible.
The object is to teach the bear to avoid people.
Like a skiff of windblown snow, the bears are abruptly God. The short season of
fear is over. The bear watches have migrated south. Their photo albums
crammed with memories.
Churchill has returned to its tranquil routine.
The bears are back in the watery world of sea ice and fat seals over which they
are such transcendent masters.
However this realm is unsettled and uncertain as its surface.
Global forces are at play the possess a power greater than that of the bears.
If the king should someday be toppled by environmental change
what would it say about the survival of the subjects.