Deep in the remote wilderness of coastal Siberia,
a phantom walks.
Known in legend as  Amur, meaning God
and devil.
We know it today as the Siberian tiger.
The tiger skirts the edge about our imagination, a symbol of strength
power and beauty.
Yet despite its fierce reputation the Siberian tiger is
dangerously close to extinction.
Less than 400 these great cats remain
in the wild.
Now wildlife biologists are using science
to save the wildest
creatures on earth.
An international team of Russian and American scientists
seeks to better understand the tiger.
Their efforts may be the tigers last best chance
as survivor. If the tiger can be saved,
it would mean protection for all that exists.
In the Shadow of the Tiger
Winters in far eastern Russia long and harsh.
Frigidaire from the heart to the continent
rips the land in snow and ice.
By late spring, tropical air of the Sea of Japan
warms the land.
Icy winters give way to golden summers
and life flourishes
A vast unbroken forest, known
as the Russian Taiga,
blankets much of the region. It is the largest
intact forest in the world
and the last stronghold for wild Siberian tigers
Weighting up to 800 pounds, the Siberian tiger is the largest cat
in the world nearly twice the size of an adult lion.
Born of snow and ice, the Siberian tiger can sprint through the forest
at fifty miles an hour.
It has thrived in this remote wilderness for thousands of years
surviving on instinct and finely honed behavior.
The Siberian tiger once numbered in the thousands
ranging from eastern Russia to South Korea,
but poaching and habitat destruction are taking their toll.
Today less than 400 Siberian tigers exist in the wild
Anf these are found almost exclusively along the narrow band of mountains and coastal
Siberia.
The Sikhote-Alin Biosphere Reserve
lies at the heart of Tiger country.
It is the largest wildlife sanctuary in the Russian Far East,
encompassing more than a thousand square miles,
a forested mountain, clear rivers and unbroken coastline.
At the edge of a forest glade, roe deer
graces. They remain alert, knowing that
out there moving silently through the forest
a cat is on the prowl.
It is a tigress seeking out for prey.
She will not make it killed today
but must soon as she has another mouth to feed.
This six month old tiger cub
its name Larisha, her mother Katia.
They are part of an in-depth study into the secretive life of Siberian tigers.
Linda Curley and John Goodrich are a husband and wife research team
coordinating the efforts at the Siberian tiger project,
a joint Russian-American study conducted by the Hornocker Wildlife Institute.
Based on the University of Idaho,
the Hornocker Institute studies threatened and endangered species around
the world.
For John and Linda, studying in tigers in Russia's remote wilderness
is the opportunity of lifetime. It baffles me that
There's actually man that exists in orange with black stripes, so
first to order,
they're beautiful. We'll get to see her very often when we do get to go inside...
makes her job everything worthwhile... you know this everything worthwhile.
I think we have a wonderful opportunity to protect tigers, to conserve tigers
and it's really exciting to be here,
a part of that and hopefully contribute to that.
I love the world, I love the world on the scene the more wild it is.
The better it is I want my favorite place in the whole world is hunting the
beach.
We're more likely to see a tiger track on the beach
than a human footprint.
When I get out on the course to have a backpack or I'm
out for weeks at a time. I'm doing what I love to me it's just as
much like occasions. It is
like work.
The thing that I love about ecobiology is learning
how other species besides humans
interact with each other xxx and
just how they make a living and I like seeing it firsthand
like being in field.
John and Linda rarely see the animals they study.
Tigers are secretive animals and you just can't... you can't just sit around
and watch them, so we have to use radio telemetry in order to answer some of
these questions and these questions are critical
to server in tiger conservation. John and Linda are using radio telemetry
unlock the Siberian tigers elusive nature. Scientists are now able to
determine
the tiger's home range size,
eating habits and social structure.
Little by little, a picture of tiger society
is a merger.
In order to use radio telemetry,
the scientists must first get a collar on the tiger.
To capture a new tiger, the scientists use thick
cabled snares. They place the snares along trails frequently used by adult
tigers.
The thick cables are ideal allowing the scientists to capture a tiger
without injuring. Snare was over the spring like that tell your clients will step on the striker.
Then the
cables attached to the tree and everything will be covered up.
Several snares have been set they will be checked daily.
Now
it's a waiting game.
Weeks can go by without a capture.
Joining the team is Russian biologist Eager Nikolai Viji.
Eager probably knows more about Siberian tigers than anyone.
He's been studying the great cat for more than 30 years.
Luck is on their side.
Only days after the snares are set, tiger
has captured. Our biggest concern is the safety of the animal.
As the animal somehow been hurt by this snare, something happened to, it
is very agitated. We stopped about 50 yards away from her.
Wad the darts into the gun.
and then approached slowly and quietly.
The first approach is the most dangerous because the scientists have no way of
telling how securely
the tiger is held in the snare. Yeah it's dangerous.
She was probably more agitated then you xxx xxx.
Gardiner and I backed to let that dart take effect because I knew even if it
wasn't enough it will calm down again and indeed it did in the second time
when she was much less mobile and and much easier to work with.
Any capture whether the tigers agitator or not,
we try to avoid eye contact, try not to approach too closely.
Stay in a little bit of cover if we can and in general try not to
present ourselves in a threatening or dominant way.
The tiger was unharmed during the capture. The team must work quickly
before the drugs wear off. Tigers
have no blank response when sedated so their eyes must be artificially
lubricated
and covered.
We start to put
fixed radio cymru which could get a radio collar as quickly as possible.
The new radio collar tier will provide the scientists with crucial information
on tiger behavior.
Ear tags are also attached
to identify the tiger in case the radio collar falls off.
We're really interested in body measurements of all kinds
and gives us a lot of information about body condition, about growth rates in animals
and differences between male and female
body parameters. When we take pad measurements
particularly the pad with because we've
also measure tracks using track measurements can help us to identify
individuals. Tiger paws
are thickly padded, allowing it to move quickly over snow
and ice. Their claws are retractable keeping them sharp
for gripping pray.
She's moving.
The tiger is showing signs that the drugs are wearing off.
The decision is made to abandon collecting more information
and move out as quickly as possible. We have radio collars on
nine president tigers and that represents just a small portion
of the entire population of Siberia tigers, but those nine animals
have radio collars will tell us so much about the population that we feel that
disturbing those nine animals will be worth the long route to protect the population as a
whole.
Tigers are not alone in this wideness. The village of Tenei
lies at the edge of the reserve.
The people here have lived with Tigers for generations.
Although Siberian tigers are not known
as man-eaters, precautions  are taken. Cattle
are herd at home in the evening and dogs stand guard
outside homes.
It is not unheard of a wounded or sick tiger
to wander into town looking for an easy meal.
However Siberian tigers prefer to stay deep in the forest
where they blend seamlessly into the landscape.
All life in the Russian Far East at here to nature's own timetable
what may start out as a few innocent flakes can turn serious
in a matter of minutes.
The Siberian tiger
was unmistakably the top predator of the Russian Far East
and for centuries it thrived here insecure
isolation.
Those days are gone
the modern world has cut its way through these ancient forests.
Logging is shrinking the Siberian tigers habitat.
The roads that logging creates leaves the tigers vulnerable to speeding cars
and poachers. Katya and Larissa
face this thread every day.
Their home ranges is bisect by the area's busiest road.
The pair must frequently cross this road while hunting.
John and Linda are concerned about Katya.
They say she is often too bold to close to the road,
other Tigers are more wary. Eleven centimeters hunt foot.
Okay so it is walking on the road down there,
probably a car came,
he ran up the back came around here
and then duck down behind the tree, so you can see where
front feet were here and that his hind leg was Ktya
out to the side right here his tail
stretches around right back here.
Probably car came, he hopped up here in duct and hide
watch the car goes by and then went back down and walked up the roof.
It is difficult for a tiger to learn the dangers of roads.
Its first encounter with a car or a poacher.
It is often its last. This tiger was killed
close to the road. The poachers skin the cat
but left its bones behind.
Perhaps unaware of their value,
the skeleton along is worth more than a year's wages
for local family. A tempting proposition for a people
in such dire economic need.
Tiger bones are highly valued on the Asian medicine market
for their ancient curative powers. This belief
as push the Siberian tiger to the brink
of extinction.
To combat the illegal trade in wildlife, anti-poaching patrols have been launched
across the region. Checkpoints are set up to look for poachers
transporting illegal wildlife. Anatolia Tavia, a
director of the Sikhote-Alin Biosphere Reserve
accompanies his man on patrol.
Setting up roadblocks and checking vehicles
is a good measure of potion prevention. If you discover a poacher,
we confiscate his preys and his gun.
It is also effective because the widely announced our intention to check certain
roles in certain day.
So many poachers who would have come here
you know. Of course poachers are still hard to reserve
but they are not as normal as they once were.
Still this is not a typical job.
The man works 24-hour shape, it is difficult
and intense more. The patrols dedication is paying off.
Poaching on the reserve is down by forty percent
but they must be ever vigilant. As long as a market for tiger bones exists,
poaching will remain a serious threat.
John Linda and field assistant Kohler Even
are traveling to Kayta's home range. Once they find her tracks
they will spend days covering large areas
following Kayta's movement.
For the next several days, this cabin will serve as base camp.
The team will head out early tomorrow morning
to look for Kayta's tracks.
We know
from radio telemetry where tiger has been
but then when the tiger leaves we have to go in there and try to figure out
where the tiger did and we do that by following their tracks are looking for
any other sign that they've left behind.
Being a field biologists and studying tigers in particular
is a lot like doing detective work.
Some blood indefinitely
welcome possibly secret.
Siberian tigers primarily feed
on wild boar deer and elk.
Tigers will often drive whatever they killed.
A short distance and often it's into
central distance cover. One of the interesting things we're trying to look
at right now is how much
tiger eats when it has not been disturbed by humans
how much they eat when they has been disturbed by human. You can see here that is
only in about sixty percent of this elk. Usually tigers
eat everything you come into a killing all you'll find is the lower legs
for lower legs and the
remains the head which is often completely chewed up.
A drawing some broken bones lying there he didn't finish this one because he
killed it very close to the road in its laying here maybe
150 meters from the road . So he got spooked by all the activity on the road
and left a lot of meat.
behind. They rely on
on stealth to capture their prey. They are
hunting technique is a stock, a short rush and they jump on the animal once they
get on animal they almost always kill it.
To survive tigers must consume 12 to 15 pounds of meat a day.
They hunt from dusk till dawn.
Keen eyesight, large cannons
sharp claws and the massive
battering ram like body enable the tiger to bring down prey
much larger than itself. Katya easily takes down five hundred-pound
wild boar.
That's nearly twice her own weight.
Much of the killing is done with her teeth.
All can see that both for lower canines were broken up
the gums. Kayta's teeth are characteristic of
much older tiger. By examining tooth photos
scientists are able to judge the approximate age of a tiger.
incisors crook. While I am out and tracking a tiger
I am just constantly visualizing what the tiger is doing.
Sometimes to the point where even kind of increasing my heartbeat and I start
getting really excited about it.
And of course added to that is
always the chance that there's going to be a tiger just around the corner.
and that there's going to be some kind of encounter just makes it
where within Katya's territory.
Measuring the print
confirms these are Kayta's tracks.
Another much smaller set of tracks indicates Kayta is traveling with her
six-month-old daughter
Larissa.
First Tiger here.
See if there's any other kind.
John and Linda have tracked Kayta for the past
three years. She has become their favorite. That's no small animal.
It marks like that track. The scientists were
even lucky enough to catch a rare glimpse of Katya.
The two of them play together and the cutoff initiated. The thing that
really surprise me
was Katya also would initiate to play and it was amazing for us to see that
the mother would be just as play for us as the couplets.
The interactions between Katya and Larissa
are important in understanding how mothers raise their young.
The time exclude their mothers
Most of their social skills that they will need for the rest life.
Because the rest so I spent
was a solitary not the company of tigers
Larissa is old enough to share kills with her mother
but still too young to hunt. She will stay with her mother for at least
another year
until she can survive on her own.
Before Katya was ready to breed, she first established a home range
or territory and spent time getting to know
her mate. Males will get together with females not just for purposes or agreement,
sometimes
will share kills and there's probably some importance
in those relationships and a male and a female knowing each other before they were
read with each other.
Katya regularly patrols more than 270 square miles
encompassing frozen lakes and weather coastline.
The female will
orient for territory based on where the food resources are,
where the the beer and the elk are.
And a male often overland his territory on one or more females.
Siberian tigers have the largest home range
then any tiger subspecies. A single male territory
can encompass more than six hundred square miles.
It's phenomenal that they can still
patrol their entire home range and keep other individuals
out of their territories. The fact that they are territorial at all and can
maintain exclusive home ranges is pretty amazing. Tigers will violate
and challenge territories and sometimes that can result in
fights and really aggressive encounters. Katya spots a intruder.
It is an unfamiliar tiger.
The encounter is brief and largely a display of dominance.
No one is injured. Katya
is lucky this time these encounters can be fatal.
Larissa
unaware of the danger. It is just as playful as ever happy to have her mother back.
Communication among tigers
is another area of great interest to John and Linda. Soon as we might think of
solitary animals is not communicating with each other.
But when they do communicate it is really important. The main form of communication
among tigers
is through scent-marking. They go around and the urinate on trees and sometimes
they
do this very frequently. Just as part of their daily activity.
This is a traditional tiger marked tree
where tiger out of xxx walk down the road here came up to the tree
turn around and spray the tree with urine. You can see this
dark spot right here where it is marked and then by this track that looks like he
also
came up in and probably scratched a little bit like this and kind of hug a
tree and
rubbed his side of his face against it. Katya uses scent marks
to advertise our presence and to mark the boundaries of her territory.
Through her scent mark, another tiger can determine Katya's age,
sex and identity. A male tiger can even tell
if she's ready to breed. This large male is responding to assent
Katya recently left. Known as flaming behavior
it is normally displayed at sites where other tigers have sprayed their scent.
This contortion
allows the smell to reach a cent organ at the back
of the tiger's mouth. Climbing trees maybe just a former exercise for Katya,
but sweat glands in her paws leave behind a cent.
Even affectionate displays between Katya and Larissa
are partly sent oriented. Rubbing
transfers and mixes body sense between familiar cats,
reinforcing and maintaining social bonds.
Katya and Larissa are providing valuable insight into tiger society.
It is time to move on but John and Linda
will return to Katya's home and continue searching for answers to the tiger's
survive.
Today the scientists will attempt a helicopter capture of a tiger named
Natashaa. The batteries on her radio collar need to be replaced
if they fail in their efforts valuable study animal will be forever
lost. Biologist Bark Liar
joins the team in this crucial effort.
Bbefore the capture before we take off
I'm just incredibly tense nervous and I think everybody is.
Once we get into the air the feeling is still very tense
but we all become so focused on what we're doing.
In general I lose my fear and a lot of my apprehension.
First thing we do is we've of course we fly to that animal's home range
and were searching for the signal. To get the signal
one hone in that animals as quickly as possible.
So everybody on the helicopter really
were cooperating just trying to get the first visual on the animal.
It's very important that the first person that sees the tiger communicates
that to someone who can
communicate to the pilots because the pilots are the ones that have to see the
tiger right away because they are certain one to xxx.
There is definitely danger involved because you're working
at such close quarters to the tops of trees
from air there's a very small cue gotten
and especially from the air because you're looking down on the back of them.
And with the animal moving in the tree,there's
usually not a big period time that you can take a
shot at you be a little narrow time frame that you can
take a shot at animal. That's usually when they stopped.
A dart doesn't fly like a bullet, a dart is affected by gravity and it's also
affected by
prop wash and the it flies more like an arrow.
This capture was a little more difficult then some other captures
because
Natasha was in the river bottom where the trees are really tall so we couldn't get
down as close to her
just we would like to. They are not really afraid
this helicopter this monster and it's a big helicopter
and this monster in the sky following them. They are not afraid of it.
They are just mad
and there would be perfectly willing to just try and pull that thing out of
the sky
if only they can reach it.
So you can get started anyway a little bit and see what kind of effect it has because
it takes
five to ten minutes for ketamine to have an effect on the
on the animal.
Our biggest concern is the animal is done. Since it looks like a stone, we
got on the ground as quickly as possible.
At that point when the animal is on the ground, every minutes is crucial.
You can't get to the and more as quick as you want. To make sure their
breathing is stabilized and also
when you are approaching an animal they're not held by a snare so there's the
possibility that the animal
will come for you.
We all share in making sure that we're monitoring respiration all the time.
Surprise,
her teeth are pretty good.
The blood and tissue samples are really important because we use them
to do genetic analysis. The information we have on
genetic analysis to compare how different Siberian tigers are from other
subspecies.
We've got to get
that really a color change so we want to make sure that the capture successful
but we
were always worried about the animal safety. That's number one.
Yeah we've been going on,
on the forest on some of the adults.
Okay we have got a tooth wear right now.
Well, we age tigers by their tooth and by tooth wear.
But having for us to have
photographs tooth we can then compare all our different tigers
at the same time.
We like to leave a tiger that's showing
some signs of getting up.
Once they start to show a little bit of head movement,
it is still going to be usually another 10 to 15 minutes before they can
really you know get up and and walk away or something at least I want.
Which is getting up. She is getting up.
OK, let's pick up quick. It's really important to get these animals
radio collar because tigers are very secretive you can
go out and sit down and watch them. With tigers you can't do that you almost
never see them.
The
information that we are getting is real important for
putting together a conservation plan. It actually could save this
the species.
When we started
our research program here in 1992 our goal
was not simply to study tigers but have a better understanding of them from a
scientific perspective.
It was to develop the best database possible for the implementation have a
conservation plans for the Siberian tiger.
Director of the Siberian tiger project Dale Migul
briefs John and Linda on the latest updates to the conservation plan. Acted
in one system of protected areas that will provide
a continuous expansive tiger habitat from the north.
Northern limits the range to very southern. It is a bold plan
ranking national parks and reserves together
to form quarter that provides absolute security
for the tiger and its prey.
Siberian tigers require an enormous amount of space.
Setting aside land for the entire population would be impossible.
Tigers and people must share the land.
Tiger conservation is not just said inside land but it's actually finding
ways for people to live
in harmony or causes coexist tigers. It means use all the resources the natural
resources in a way that does not damage them.
They works with community members to implement tiger conservation
on the local level.
The survival of tigers
and conservation general is very closely linked to
the well-being of people. If people feel they are a sense of well-being that their
economic need to be met that I can return to the fourth resources
and extract them
in such an intense a fashion as when they feel they're being stressed. Conservation.
will succeed
only if the people of the region see the tiger as a creature worth saving.
It is late autumn of Russian Far East.
Time of change.
One year has come and gone since the scientists first saw
Katya and the Larissa in the wild.
Larissa is now an adult tigress. She has stayed close to home
taking over part of Kayta's territory.
Like her mother, Larissa has marked the boundaries of her range.
She has even found a mate, a radio collared tiger
named Jenny.
Tigers can live in jungles. Tigers can live in swampland. Tigers can live
in arboreal forest.
Border is critical where those arguments xxx.
So when we ask how do we save tigers how do we save tiger habitat we're really asking
how do we save habitat for the XXX on which tiger survive.
Wild boar make up more than fifty percent of the tigers diet
or feed on Korean pine nuts
which are abundant in the dense forest  of Sikhote-Alin.
Korean pine is also a highly value timber source.
Large numbers of these trees have been cut from the tiger and although now
protected
illegal logging of Korean pine continues to this day.
Dale in Russian biologists Sasha Mutual Inc are trying to determine what the
tiger's pray
needs to survive.
You have a good answer on tiger biology, means understanding the relationship between
tigers the animals that also occur in the forest.
Their relationship between dear know
wild boar and bear.
Understanding that a more complex is a first step to understanding
what tigers needed to survive. Biologists with the Hornocker Wildlife Institute
hope to paint a complete picture tiger ecology.
The long-term survival of wild Siberian tigers
is dependent on the success of countless plants and animals.
Larissa's mate Jenny has spent the last three days in one area.
He moved on early this morning. Linda and Cola are going in to investigate
what Jenny left behind.
The two researchers expect to find the remains of the tiger's kill.
What they discover shocks them both.
When we first walked into that kill side of course we're expecting to
find an elk or bore, the usual food item of a tiger.
Who was pretty shocking when we look down inside
tiger paws.
The researchers must now determine the identity of the
tiger
and how it died. Linda fears
the dead tiger is Larissa.
With multiple blood here on her nose was like she come off the kill.
Maybe bone was broken. Four ribs broken.
We were looking at her claws because they were black
and they were eroded at me and as if she had been drugged
on the asphalt. Coal and Linda are confused by their findings,
broken bones, ripped flash, tar
In the fur a tiger did not kill this animal.
Right now I suspect that this is Katya Katya's
twenty-month-old cobe who's been on our own for the last
several months not traveling with Katya
which is a bit confusing right now because we know that they've also spent time
together.
This cub and Jenny they've shared kills we suspected that they made it so I'm
not sure
what's going on but we need to do a search the area more
seeking to find a few more bones, seeking to find some more tracks.
You try to piece the puzzle together, we work with this animal every day
that's our job is to track these animals become like part of our family
and we know so much about him though we rarely see them.
All over radio collared tigers are like
individuals to us and so when something happens to one of them.
It becomes a very a personal thing.
and personal loss.
The dead tiger is Larissa, Kayta's
only daughter. The young tigress John and Linda knew so well
is dead.
We knew exactly
when the cub was conceived. We knew exactly when the cub born.
Although we never had a radio collar on the cub we followed it through
the first two years. So it is like from
was still traveling with Katya and after that kept calling it through
tracking in the snow. So we're losing this cub
losing alive information.
Linda and Cola investigation leads them to the road,
we determined that the animal was hit by a car, actually hit by a large truck
the tracks start here. It's like the hitter and drug her
under the back tires all the way to here. That's about 15 meters.
The driver then picked up Larissa's
limp
bloody body, dragged her to the side of the road
and threw her down the gully.
Larissa's mate Jenny found the young tigress.
Tracks show that he carried her more than 200 yards,
an incredible distance to a clearing in the forest.
Jenny stayed with the Larissa for three days
before leaving. The fact that
the animal died a senseless death because somebody was driving too fast
on the road. That makes me angry.
This is the only road through the reserve and it goes right through the
middle
of one of the most productive home ranges reserve. But because
of this road
every single tiger that has been born in this area for at least the last eight
years
has died as a result either being hit by cars
or being shot by poachers from the road.
There are times like this when the future of wild Siberian tigers
seems lost. Yet in Siberia it is said
hope this is last to die despite all odds
the number of wild Siberian tigers is on the rise
from a low 250 in 1992
to an estimated 350 today.
The tiger especially the Siberian tiger is perhaps the ultimate symbol
wildness the ultimate symbol of perhaps are linked to nature.
Everybody is enamored
or afraid or some way has some kind of relationship to attack whether the
they'd seen one in the wild if they live with their tigers or not
Children know about tigers won the first animal they learn about.
He is retiring if we can't save an animal with that strong
cultural symbol not only for Russia for the whole world, it comes
down to ask a question whether we would save ourselves so we need to save
the tiger.
As much for its own sake it's for our own.
Their beauty was the treasure, a jewel on this earth
that we should protect. I can't image life on this earth
without other creatures so exquisitely.
It's clear an opportunity exists
to save Russia's greatest treasure not just in myth and legend
but as it has lived for centuries stalking the snowy peaks and river
valleys
of the Russian Far East, a place
and the people that live in the shadow
of the time.